<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse wherin is debated whether it be expedient that the scripture should be in English for al men to reade that wyll Fyrst reade this booke with an indifferent eye, and then approue or condempne, as God shall moue your heart.</title>
            <author>Standish, John, 1507?-1570.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1554</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 82 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12919</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23207</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117827</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853037</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853037</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18399</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12919)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18399)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 332:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse wherin is debated whether it be expedient that the scripture should be in English for al men to reade that wyll Fyrst reade this booke with an indifferent eye, and then approue or condempne, as God shall moue your heart.</title>
                  <author>Standish, John, 1507?-1570.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[168] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In ædibus Roberti Caly, typographi,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Excusum Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>mense Decembris. Anno. 1554.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: I.S., i.e. John Standish.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title: Cum priuilegio.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K L⁴.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Versions --  English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18399:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18399:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A diſcourſe wherin is debated whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be expedient that the ſcripture ſhould be in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh for al men to reade that wyll.</p>
            <p>¶Fyrſt reade this booke with an indifferent eye, and then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue or condempne, as God ſhall moue your heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non quis dicat, ſed quid dicat animaduertas velim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>¶EXCVSVM LONDINI IN aedibus Roberti Caly, Typographi: Menſe Decembris Anno. <hi>1554.</hi> Cum priuilegio.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:18399:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18399:2"/>
            <head>¶A queſtion to be moued to the highe courte of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether it be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhoulde be in the vulgare tonge for al men to reade at their pleaſure withoute re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraynt? Yea, or whether it may wel be permitted ſo to be? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderynge on the one parte, the manifold inconueniences which haue ſprong therby theſe yeres paſte, as obſtinacie, diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, fleſhely libertie, loſſe of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, ſwarmes of errours, and hereſies, with damnation of thouſande ſoules: and on the other parte weyenge diſcretlye
<pb facs="tcp:18399:3"/> not onelye the great difficultie that is in ſcripture with the cauſes thereof, but alſo diuerſe and ſundrie moſt manifeſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations, whiche fully perſuade that the ſcripture by no meanes ought to be ſuffred to be in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye mans hande in the vulgare tonge for all men to deſcant vp on &amp; to wraſte after their fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye appetites: which all appeare euidentlye to be moſte true, by that whiche is here ſet furth in this proceſſe. That is to ſaye: in theſe ſixe chapters folowing.
<list>
                  <label>The fyrſt.</label>
                  <item>The ſcripture is very harde to be vnderſtande.</item>
                  <label>The ſeconde.</label>
                  <item>God woulde the ſcripture to be obſcure &amp; harde, &amp; the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries not to be playne to al men.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18399:3"/>
                  <label>The thyrde.</label>
                  <item>Sundrie cauſes wherof the hardnes in ſcripture doth come.</item>
                  <label>The fourth.</label>
                  <item>Howe many wayes the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doeth kyll.</item>
                  <label>The fifth.</label>
                  <item>The beſt meanes to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande ſcripture by.</item>
                  <label>The ſixte.</label>
                  <item>Fiftie probations that ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ought not to be in engliſh.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe to the entent none ſhoulde haue occaſion to miſconſtrue the trew meanyng herof, it is to be thought that if all men were good and catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, then were it lawfull, yea and verye profitable alſo, that the ſcripture ſhoulde be in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe, ſo that the tranſlation were trewe and faythfull: But
<pb facs="tcp:18399:4"/> neyther all the people be good and catholike, nor the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions trewe and faythfull. As for the common tranſlations, whiche haue been vſed in moſte mennes handes, are ſo full of faultes, that to correcte and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them wer euen as a man woulde goe aboute to ſowe vp euery hole in a nette to make it a whole clothe. Yea and yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide this, yf your enemye ſhould geue you bread, which ye knew well he hadde poyſoned before, would ye not be afrayd (though it be after ſcraped neuer ſo cleane) to eate of it? At al times heretikes haue laboured to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte the ſcriptures, that they might ſerue for their noughtye purpoſes to confirme theyr er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours therwith, as Dionyſe bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe
<pb facs="tcp:18399:4"/> of Corinth teſtifieth: but ſpeciallye nowe in our tyme, O good Lorde, howe haue the tranſlatours of the Bible into Engliſhe purpoſelye corrupted the textes, oft maliciouſly put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge in ſuche wordes as might in the readers eares ſerue to the profe of ſuche hereſies as they went aboute to ſow? Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che be not onely ſet furth in the tranſlations, but alſo in certain Prologues and gloſes added therevnto. And theſe thynges thei haue ſo handled (as in dede it is no greate maiſtrie to doe) with probable reaſons verye apparent to the ſimple and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, that an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre of innocentes they haue ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituallye poyſoned and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted within this realme, &amp; cauſed
<pb facs="tcp:18399:5"/> them to periſhe obſtinatlye.</p>
            <p>Nowe for the other parte, all the people, namelye the feruent readers of ſcripture in Engliſh, be not onely not good, but the moſte parte of them be ſtarke noughte, ſo frowarde, ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe, ſo leude, and ſo wicked, that they be euer readye to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert that whiche is good, and to take a ſelfe wyllye opinion, contrarye to the true ſenſe of ſcripture and meaninge of tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ghoſt, as God knoweth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hath ſhewed euer ſince the Bibles were ſet vp in chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, common for all men that woulde to reade.</p>
            <p>But yf all men (I ſaye) were good and catholike, and the tranſlations trewe and fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bible in Engliſh (though
<pb facs="tcp:18399:5"/> it be nowe muche hurtfull) then might be muche profitable.</p>
            <p>And that is the cauſe that the Clergie did agree (as it is in a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitution prouincial) that the Bibles which were tranſlated into Engliſhe before Wycliffes dayes might be ſuffred: ſo that only ſuch had them in handling as were allowed by the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and approued mete readers thereof, &amp; that their readynge ſhoulde be onely to the ſettinge furthe of Goddes glorie. For thoughe ſcripture to good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be a noriſher of vertue, and to them that bee noughte the meane of amendment, and for him that is whole, liuely foode, and for him that is ſicke, euen as a medicine: yet often tymes we ſee that one ſtomacke ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="tcp:18399:6"/> harme of that meat wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of another taketh profit, and that whiche helpeth one ſicke man hurteth another. Some men mighte be admitted to the readynge of S. Mathewes ghoſpell, whiche yet be not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble well to wey the ghoſpell of S. Iohn. Manye hable to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe the actes of the Apoſtles, whiche be farre vnmete to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with Thapocalyps. Many might be allowed to handle the Epiſtle to the Coloſſians, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che be to weake for the Epiſtle to the Romaines. The father ofte permitteth to one of his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a knife to cut his meate withal, wheras he taketh from another of hys children (fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeyng his wantonnes) the knife for feare of cutting his fingers.
<pb facs="tcp:18399:6"/> Manye in theſe our miſerable dayes nowe paſt haue ſo miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rablie abuſed the ſcriptures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the meaninge of tholye ghoſt, that vnder the colour of great zeale and good affection they haue peruerted and wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted all amiſſe. Yea and ſcantly two of them haue in all poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes wel agreed together: neuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theleſſe in this one poynt they all euer agreed. That is to ſay, to deſtroye vtterlye all vnitie and comely order, all holye ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, all holye prayers and faſtinges, with all godlye deuotion.</p>
            <p>And yet beſide this, nothing ſhould ſooner cauſe vs to iudge that ſcripture ought not to be in Engliſh for euery one to read and deſcant vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wyll, then
<pb facs="tcp:18399:7"/> to ſee that the buſie readers be euer for the moſte parte of the wycked ſorte: ſuche be euer bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie bodies to diſpute and reaſon (but al w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out reaſon) of thinges farre paſſing their capacities: where as S. Gregory Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen rebuketh all thoſe, ſaying, that onely Moyſes aſcended vp into the hyll &amp; ſpake with God,<note place="margin">Exod.</note> but the people taryed beneth &amp; receiued the lawes &amp; preceptes that they ſhould kepe, and the pointes that thei ſhuld beleue at him, ſaiyng vnto him (as would god our leude goſpellers would nowe ſay to the true preachers) heare you God, and let vs heare you. Saint Hierome alſo in his tyme greatly complayneth that the comen ignorant people did preſume to medle with the
<pb facs="tcp:18399:7"/> miſteries of ſcripture<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſeing that ſaint Paule ſheweth that tholy ghoſt ſo ordeyned his churche that he wold haue ſome reders and ſome hearers, ſome techers and ſome learners. But theſe quite turne vp ſide doune the right ordre of Chriſtes churche, the one part medling with the others office: &amp; the more blinde the more bolde, the more igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunte the more buſie, the leſſe witte the more inquiſitiue, the more leude the more bablynge of great doubtes and high que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of Chriſtes Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and of his priuye and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearcheable myſteries, and that oft moſt preſumptuouſly with out al reuerence or godly feare, bothe at drinkinge and eating, as though it were but a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburye
<pb facs="tcp:18399:8"/> tale, and that when the ale is in the witte is oute. Then flowe furthe manye er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and hereſies. Then are the ſimple catched in the ſnare of the Deuyll without hope of recouerie. And all this (alas and woe is me) haue we ful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perince of in theſe yeares paſte. But nowe, thankes bee to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte, that by his onelye might and power, when it was paſte all mans helpe, hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered vs from the Deuill and the bondage of Pharao, and brought vs furthe of darknes of ſciſmes and hereſies into the cleare light of the trueth againe by ſendynge vs oure bleſſed queene Mary (euen another <hi>Helena</hi> to bringe againe the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye croſſe) whiche euen from her
<pb facs="tcp:18399:8"/> infancie hath ſticked faſte and cleued ſurelye vnto the ſounde piller of trueth (the catholyke churche) whiche wyll neuer faile: ſhe hathe euer defended it to the vttermoſt of her power. Lorde graunt her longe life to continue the ſame, and graunte her ioyfull deliueraunce of her moſte comfortable burden.</p>
            <p>When God of his great mercye ſente her to be our liege ladye, our quene and gouerneſſe, then we receyued of him as great a benefit, as euer did the Iſraeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Heſter or Iudith. O lord, before her comminge, the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che was troden downe and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully (ſpitfully I might ſaye) ſpoyled, by might, by tiranny &amp; hereſy: the great Deuyl was let loſe, al was quite plucked vp by
<pb facs="tcp:18399:9"/> the rotes, vnder the colour and falſe name of vice ſuperſtition and ydolatrie, they vtterlye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed all deuotion, all vertue, and godlye religion. The feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Serpent Python, that gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous dragon with manye hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des mencioned of in the Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips, did ſtill perſecute the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the ſun: That is to ſay, our mother the church, deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge her children here in this realme inceſſauntly, tyll Gods merciful pitie, gods pitiful mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy did electe &amp; ſend this bleſſed woman Mary our Queene in ſtede of Michael tharcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gel to ouerthrow him, &amp; to reſtore his temple and furniſhe agayne his houſe, which now of late with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe .xxii. yeares was here in Englande worſe ſpoiled and
<pb facs="tcp:18399:9"/> defaced then euer was his tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple at Hieruſalem, eyther by the Chaldies, or by Antiochus. Marye therefore oure noble queene, God him ſelfe dyd ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointe euen as he did Ioſue, Eſdras, or Iudas Machabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us to bringe vs into the ryghte waye agayne towarde the land of promiſe (for we were farre ſtrayed amiſſe throughe ſynne, auarice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and lecherye) and to reedifie his temple through her wiſedome, ſhe beynge the perfit mirrour and pearle of all chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian queenes and princes. Yea, and if the olde prouerbe be true (as it is moſt true in dede) whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſayeth, euery prince is to his realme &amp; ſubiectes, ether a very precious Iuell, or els a deadlye poyſon, becauſe ſuche as the
<pb facs="tcp:18399:10"/> prince is, ſuche will the people laboure to be, whether it be in vertue or vice. What a precious Iewell then haue we receyued of God, in receyuynge her noble eſtate to be our ladye &amp; queene, an example of all vertue, deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and prayer, a ſpectacle to al realmes? And ſuerly the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon voice is that her grace is not onelye moſte noble, moſte vertuous, moſte wittie, and moſte ſtudious, but alſo moſte excellent in learning, farre paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge eyther the noble Romai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, <hi>Cornelia</hi> &amp; <hi>Hortenſia,</hi> or the godly learned wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of whom S. Hierome writeth <hi>Euſtochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Paula</hi> and <hi>Bleſilla.</hi> Therefore if queene <hi>Saba</hi> iuſtlye ſayde it was a ſigne that God loued his people,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Barall. 9.</note> for ſendynge them
<pb facs="tcp:18399:10"/> Salomon to raygne ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, maye not we as iuſtly now ſay the ſame to Englande? And yf the wiſdome, pietie, and vertue, of Onias was ſayde to be the cauſe of the proſperous eſtate of their citie,<note place="margin">2. Mach. 2.</note> ſhall not we like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſaye to this our realme? Beſides this,<note place="margin">Roma. 12.</note> if gouernours be highlye prayſed in ſcripture, whiche rule with great ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and carefulneſſe, what ſhal we then ſaye to her, whiche for all our wealthes bothe bodilye and ghoſtly is ſtyll moſte vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant and carefull? And finallye nowe to conclude, if amonge the heathen, the noble Princes haue euer highlye been extolled for ſundrie vertues, howe high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is ſhe worthie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for ſo plentifull and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifolde
<pb facs="tcp:18399:11"/> kindes of vertue?</p>
            <p>Whiche doeth not onely excell in godlyneſſe, in deuotion, in prayer, in faſtyng, in abſtinence, in humilitie, in charitie, in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, pitie, and compaſſion, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, in knowledge, in wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, in excellencie of witte, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of no ſmall ſtudie in godly literature, but beinge of exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite learnynge, of profounde knowledge, &amp; of exacte iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, beſide notable diligence and great painfulneſſe euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her childhode (as for her polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and affayres of the realme, in ſettinge furthe the wealthe and commoditie thereof, and in defendinge vs from outwarde and inwarde enemies I ſpeake not of) but alſo whiche doeth farre paſſe all other (as it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently
<pb facs="tcp:18399:11"/> ſeen) in her moſt godly innated zeale, that ſhe beareth ſtyll moſte earneſt towarde the vnitie and faythe of Chriſtes trew religion, and towarde the cheife head therof vnder Chriſt whiche by the ſpace of theſe xx. yeres, euen tyll ſhe came, was baniſhed this realme, throughe ſciſme and hereſie, through co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes and letcherye, Lorde be mercifull vnto vs.</p>
            <p>Wherfore if in the Goſpel of. S Luke many holy wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and zeale toward Chriſtes church be highly pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by name, &amp; likewiſe in tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes of the Apoſtles, and in the laſte Chapter to the Romans: yea and if. S. Hierom wrote a whole booke of ſuche holye and vertuous women, what leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:18399:12"/> prayſe is her highnes worthye now to haue, being inferiour to none of the all? being euin now amonge al princeli wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the worlde a verye Phenix. But I wyll let this paſſe: I wyl ſay no more but only this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the dough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter maye welbe knowen by the Mother, and that as we fell from all goodnes at the moſte vniuſt fall of her Mother that moſt noble Lady Queene Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theryn: So doe we nowe riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne at the moſte iuſte riſinge agayne of her noble eſtate to the Crowne of Englande: So that in her moſte godlye perſon is ſhut vp all our worldly ioye, comfort, and hope, whom with her moſt noble &amp; vertuous huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande, Philip our Lord &amp; King (not much inferiour to her high<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:18399:12"/> in grace, vertue, and godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as credible menne reporte) Ieſu longe proſper in honoure, grace, and vertue daylye increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge. But nowe to the proceſſe intendid,</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The fyrſt Chaptre.</hi> Scripture is very harde to be vnderſtande.</head>
               <p>IF nothing els ſhuld moue the Scripture to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> furthe of the irreuerente and lewde handling of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, this one thing were ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, to conſider the great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, the great obſcurity and hardnes, that all the aunciente writers with one conſente af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme to be in Scripture: yea
<pb facs="tcp:18399:13"/> Scripture it ſelf graunteth the ſame. <hi>Scrutamini Scripturas,</hi> ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the ſcriptures (ſayth Chriſt) but if they haue nede of a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teney,<note place="margin">Ioan. viii.</note> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be not eaſy: chriſt wold not ſo haue bid if thei had bene light. Nor Peter wolde haue ſayde manye thinges be harde to be vnderſtand in Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les epiſtles, which then the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did peruerte (ſaythe he) as they did other Scriptures to their condemnacion. And what dyd Paule meane of the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Scripture whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he cried <hi>O Altitudo diuitiarum. &amp;c.</hi> O the depnes,<note place="margin">Rom. xi.</note> O the heigth of the ſecretes of God.</p>
               <div type="testimonies">
                  <head>Herken now the teſtimonies of of auncient writers concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge this matter.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18399:13"/>
                  <p>GReg. Nazian. ſayeth: <hi>Non cuiuſuis chriſtiani eſt de dei myſterijs diſſerere,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Greg. Naz. li. primo theol. ſuae.</note> 
                     <hi>non adeo res hec eſt vilis, &amp;c.</hi> It is not for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye Chriſtian to diſpute of the miſteries of god, the matter is not ſo vile. &amp;c. Agayne he ſayth:<note place="margin">Greg. Naz. in appollogia et Hier. in proaemio in Ezech.</note> 
                     <hi>Non oim librorum ſacrae ſcripturae tractatio omnibus aetatibus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur apud hebraeos,</hi> the Iewes did not admitte all men to the readinge of Scripture co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe the great difficultye and highe myſteryes therin.</p>
                  <div type="testimony">
                     <head>The teſtimony of S. Ambroſe.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Scriptura diuina magnum mare eſt habens in ſe abiſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſenſuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundorum. &amp;c,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ambr. lib. vii Epiſt. xliiii.</note> The holi Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (ſayeth he) is a great Sea hauing depnes without botom
<pb facs="tcp:18399:14"/> of many profound ſenſes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Two teſtimonies of Chriſoſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Nihil eſt in ſcriptura quod non multas ſenſuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habet diuitias:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Chriſoſt. hom xxi. in Gen.</note> 
                        <hi>ne<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> enim vel ſyllaba vel apiculus eſt in ſacris litteris in cuius profu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do non ſit nobis quiſpiam magnus theſau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rus.</hi> There is nothing in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (ſayeth he) but it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyneth great ſpirituall treſure through the manifolde ſenſes: there is neither ſyllable nor letter wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in ſome great riches is not hid. O what difficultie is then in it? Can it then be turmoyled of al, as it muſt nedes be, being ſtil in thengliſhe tranſlation?</p>
                     <p>More ouer he ſayth. <hi>In Sacris literis nihil eſt quod non ingente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſaurum contineat modo ſcruta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem habeat.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Hom xxi. et xxiiii. in Gen.</note> 
                        <hi>At no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cuiuis contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git
<pb facs="tcp:18399:14"/> adire Corynthum.</hi> There is nothinge in ſcripture, but it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth greate treaſure, ſo that there be a dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſearcher. How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beit, it is not for euery one to ſearche furthe the ſecretes or difficulties.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="testimony">
                     <head>Diuers teſtimonies of S. Hiero.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Scriptura ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis obſcuritatibꝰ et fu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> typis obuolutae<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Hier. ad Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaſ. tom. iii.</note> 
                        <hi>vt ols in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretatione egeat. Eſt porta orie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis de qua verum lume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exoritur, quae clauſa eſt communi populo et ſoli illi patet, qui habet clauem Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid. et ce.</hi> Scripture is wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped (ſaieth he) in ſo great dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and figures of thinges to come, that it hath all nede of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation. It is the eaſt gate (that Ezechiell ſpeaketh of) whereout the true light dothe ſpring, which is euer ſhut to the
<pb facs="tcp:18399:15"/> comen people, and is onely open to him that hathe the keye of Dauid. &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="testimony">
                     <head>An other teſtimonie of S. Hiero.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Hie. de cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicis epiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis.</note>
                        <hi>Iacobus, Ioannes, Petrus, &amp; Iudas. vii. Epiſtolas ſcripſerunt ſuccinctas &amp; breues in uerbis, ſed longas in ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentijs, ut rarus ſit qui in earum lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione non caecutiat, Apoca. Ioannis tot habet ſacramenta quot uerba<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> Iames, Iohan, Peter, &amp; Iude (ſaieth he) wrote .vii. Epiſtels, quicke &amp; breffe in wordes, but long in ſenſe, that fewe there be whiche doe not erre in readinge of them Thapocalyps of ſaint Iohn, is as full of myſteries as of wordes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="testimony">
                     <head>An other teſtimonie of S. Hiero.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18399:15"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fateor me nun<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> in diuinis uo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminibus proprijs uiribus credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſe et ce.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Hie. in prolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go in Parali.</note> I confeſſe (ſaieth he) that I durſt neuer credit myne owne wytte, in triyng the ſenſe of ſcripture, but euer ſearched of other &amp;c. But what place of ſcripture durſt not our men in theſe daies take in hande? And all throughe thengliſhe tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, awaye with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="testimony">
                     <head>Yet an other teſtimonie of S. Hierom.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Totum quod legimus in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>et quidem &amp; fulget in cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rice, ſed dulcius in medulla eſt:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Hier. ad pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>linum.</note> 
                        <hi>qui edere vu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t nucleum frangat nuce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Reuela (inquit Dauid) oculos me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os, et conſiderabo mirabilia de lege tua.</hi> Al that we rede in ſcripture (ſaieth he) dothe floriſh &amp; ſhine
<pb facs="tcp:18399:16"/> in the letter: but it is much ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the ſpirituall ſenſe. He the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that will eate the curnel let him breake the ſhelle. And Dauid ſaied. Open thou mine eyes (O lorde) geue thou me knowledge &amp; I ſhall vnderſtande the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull myſteries of thy lawe. Marke then hereby the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="testimony">
                     <head>The teſtimonie of Cyrill.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Cyrill lib. v. in leuit.</note>
                        <hi>Ex hoſtiis quae offeruntur et con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceduntur ſacerdotibus, pars igni traditur et ſic deo offertur, vt ſcia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ꝙ nobis aliqua ex ſcriptura apprehendere et cognoſcere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceditur: aliqua tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t quae deo re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeruantur. &amp; ce.</hi> Of the ſacrifices of tholde lawe (ſayeth he) parte was geuen to the prieſtes, but
<pb facs="tcp:18399:16"/> part was committed to the fire and ſo reſerued to God. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we maye vnderſtande, that parte of ſcripture is geuen to vs to apprehende and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, &amp; part is reſerued onely to the knowledge of God, as appeareth more playnlye in the laſte ſentence, but one, of this chapter.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="testimony">
                     <head>The teſtimonie of Damaſcene.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quaedam in ſacris literis quae de deo traduntur ſunt effabilia,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Damaſ. lib. i. Capi. ii.</note> 
                        <hi>quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ineffabilia: quaedam cognoſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilia et quaedam incognoſcibilia.</hi> Some thinges in ſcripture (ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he) concernynge God maye be ſpoken as that God did cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the worlde: ſome maye not be ſpoken, as thunitie of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce with trinitie of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb facs="tcp:18399:17"/> and the eternall genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſonne, whiche none can expreſſe ſayeth Eſay: ſome maye be knowen as that God is eternall, God is incorporeal, but ſome can not be knowen, as of the iudgementes of God. O what great depeneſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out botome?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="testimony">
                     <head>The teſtimonie of Eraſmus.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Eraſ. in eccle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiaſt. lib. iii.</note>
                        <hi>Sunt qui fortiter negant in cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicis libris vllam ineſſe obſcurita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, modo aſſit peritia ſermonis, et ſanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudiciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> opinioni ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctenus certe fauco, vt optarim eſſe veriſſimam: ſed vna voce recla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant omnes eccleſiae doctores: et in his ij quo<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> qui nec linguarum peritia, nec ſano iudicio carueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> There be whiche denye anye
<pb facs="tcp:18399:17"/> hardneſſe to be in ſcripture, ſo that right iudgement and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge in the tongues be not lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge. And ſurelye hitherto I haue ſo euer fauoured this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that I haue wiſhed it to be moſte true, but all the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the church crie againſt it with one voyce: yea euen thei whiche neyther lacked good iudgement, nor connynge in the tongues.</p>
                     <p>Finally all thauncient holye writers affirme that nothynge is nowe commaunded in the newe teſtament, but the ſame was commaunded in tholde. <hi>Nec quicquam eſſe geſtum quod non ſit vel a Prophetis praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, vel typis adumbratum.</hi> And that there is nothing done now in the newe, but the ſame was
<pb facs="tcp:18399:18"/> eyther ſpoken before by the prophetes, or els darkelye ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed in figures. Oh is there not then greate hardeneſſe in ſcripture? More ouer, the auncient writers doe affirme that neuer man was able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuſſe fullye al the myſteries of ſcripture, and that tholy ghoſt would them not fully to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, as the times, the conſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the worlde &amp;c. And the middeſt of the ſeconde chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the .ij. Epiſtle of Paule to the Theſſalonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. (<hi>Tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net teneat &amp;c. donec de medio fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at.</hi> Whiche place S. Auguſtine plainly confeſſeth that he doeth not vnderſtande). The begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge of S. Iohns Ghoſpell, Thappocalyps, the beginning of Ezechiell about the wheles,
<pb facs="tcp:18399:18"/> and from the xl. chapter the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions &amp; dimenſions of the temple. &amp;c. Yea and beſide this howe manye places be in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture not eaſie to be perceiued of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnlearned? As that of Paule:<note place="margin">Phillip. i.</note> I do fulfil that which lacked in Chriſtes paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c. Worke your ſaluation &amp;c.<note place="margin">Phillip. ii.</note> Doe not theſe to the ſimple ſeeme very blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie? With many hundred tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes as harde as theſe.</p>
                     <p>All this nowe well conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (concerninge the contentes of this firſt chapter) and with indifferent eares hearde, and euery thing that is here ſpoken weyed to the bottom, hauynge a godly zeale to Chriſtes flock, doe you thinke it expedient, yea or tollerable for all leude and wicked without reſtraynte to
<pb facs="tcp:18399:19"/> be iudges and arbitrers vpon ſcripture, as they wyll nedes be if it be in the vulgare tongue?</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſeconde Chapter</hi> God woulde the Scripture to be obſcure, and the myſteries not to be playne to al men.</head>
               <p>CHriſt ofte ſo mingled hys communication (ſayeth E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmus in the preface of Matthew) that I think his wil and pleaſure was to bee harde, and not to be vnderſtande. Yea, there be certayne places (ſayeth he) almoſt not poſſible to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded: and yet God woulde his ſecretes to be ſo hidde from the wicked and ignoraunte by tropes, figures, and other
<pb facs="tcp:18399:19"/> obſcurities (leſt lyke ſwyne thei ſhoulde treade downe pearles) that yet ſufficient light myght be opened &amp; ſhewed to the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, learned, &amp; godly. Againe God would for our exerciſe, for our labour, for our ſtudie, and diligence,<note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. de doctrina chriſt. cap.</note> the myſteries to bee ſought furth not without great difficultie, that they might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare moore precious beynge deare bought.</p>
               <p>Moreouer God ordeyned ſuche obſcuritie and hardeneſſe to be hidde in tropes and alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories, that the high myſteries might more clearly ſhyne furth of cloudes and darkeneſſe.</p>
               <p>Beſide this, as the ſon beame geueth more heate agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt glaſſe or plate, ſo doe ofte the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of ſcripture moore delite,
<pb facs="tcp:18399:20"/> and geue more ſpirituall heate beynge ſearched &amp; tryed furth of darcke cloudes and thycke ſhadowes.</p>
               <p>Finallye God this ordeyned for that he would not man to be to buſy in triyng aboue hys capacitie, as the two penye do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours haue euer been. <hi>Beatus homo qui ſemper eſt pauidus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bleſſed is he that euer kepeth a godly feare. <hi>Nolite altu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſapere nec ſapere pluſquam oportet.</hi> Be not to wiſe in your owne eyes. The wiſe man ſaide not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe: <hi>alti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ra te ne quaeſieris.</hi> Seke not aboue thy reach. For thinke ſurely that they whiche goe aboute to apprehende the high myſteries, do folowe as it wer to ouertake their own ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes: the faſter they folowe,
<pb facs="tcp:18399:20"/> the faſter it ſlippeth awaye.</p>
               <p>Marke alſo that it was not without highe myſterie, that God reproued Eſdras for ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge to highe in his ſecretes:<note place="margin">iiii. Eſd. iiii. iiii. Eſd. xii.</note> and in another place, bad him open his myſteries only to the wiſe. And againe it was not without highe myſterye that God woulde not ſuffer the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to aſcende into the mounte,<note place="margin">Exod.</note> nor the wicked to builde vp the tower of Babilon ſo highe as they woulde.<note place="margin">Geneſ.</note> Thinke that her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ignoraunt multitude are taught not to climbe to hyghe into Gods ſecretes and priuie myſteries. Remembre (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche you) howe Thiſraelites coulde not behold Moyſes face for brightneſſe.<note place="margin">ii. Cor. iii.</note> And conſider likewyſe howe Dionyſe ſainct
<pb facs="tcp:18399:21"/> Paules diſciple, ſayeth, yf thou canſt not well loke vp to the ſhinyng of the ſunne with open eyes, but they wyll daſell, and thou muſt hold vp thine hande betwene thine eye and the ſon: how many handes then haddeſt thou nede to holde vp, yf thou ſhouldeſt behold the vnſearche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able myſteries of the ſunne of righteouſneſſe God hym ſelfe? The ſhinyng beames of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye influence thou canſt not beholde, but as it were vnder a cloude.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. viii. Math. xi. and xiii. Iohn. xv. Rom. xi. and xvi. Epheſ. i. and .vi. Col. i. &amp; .ii. Phil. iiii.</note>Marke well, it was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out greate cauſe, that bothe Chriſt and Paule oft do ſpeake of myſteries. As in Luke, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewe, &amp; Iohn: And in the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to the Romaines, to the Epheſians, to the Coloſſians,
<pb facs="tcp:18399:21"/> and Philippians.</p>
               <p>Conſider alſo with howe great feare and reuerence the myſteries ought to be touched,<note place="margin">Phil. iiii.</note> yea and that onely of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men. And ponder ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtlye with youre ſelfe howe Chriſt woulde his myſteries to be opened but to fewe <hi>(myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterium eſt archanum vel ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum dei conſilium paucis cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ſeu occultum dei iudicium at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tum)</hi> neyther to the wicked, nor yet to the infirme that be not able to weye them. Yea and that manye myſteries be receyued in the churche of Chriſt, whiche neuer were writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten, as S. Baſil witneſſeth.</p>
               <p>Beſide this S. Dionyſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:<note place="margin">Dion. in cael. hier. cap. iii.</note> 
                  <hi>Decentiſsimum eſt myſticis ſcripturarum eloquijs ſacram et
<pb facs="tcp:18399:22"/> obſtruſam caeleſtiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpirituum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritat<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m archanis velamentis et ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratiſsimis ſignis occultare.</hi> It is moſt decent to hide the holye &amp; vnſearcheable veritie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſprites in the myſtical ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kinges of ſcripture with ſecret coueringes &amp; moſt holy ſignes.</p>
               <p>And S. Auguſtine affirmeth, that <hi>ſacrae ſcripturae obſcuritas cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuerſas pariat ſententias vtilis eſt,</hi> the darkeneſſe of holy ſcripture when it bringeth furth diuerſe ſenſes then is it profitable.</p>
               <p>This gere our newe fangled readers doe ſmally paſſe vpon. Therfore it can not be choſen, but the Engliſhe tranſlations whiche haue been the occaſion of moſt miſchiefe muſt nedes be taken awaye.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The thirde Chapter.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18399:22"/> Sundrie cauſes wherof oftymes difficultie and great hardnes in ſcripture doeth ariſe.</head>
               <p>THe cauſes whereof ofty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes the great difficultie in ſcripture doeth ariſe,<note place="margin">j.</note> are very many: one is, for that there be ſo manye tropes, figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and darke ſayinges in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>Another is,<note place="margin">ij.</note> hardnes in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ofte doeth ariſe of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie of the tongue, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye tongue hath his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per phraſe not perfitlye to bee knowen beinge tranſlated into another tongue.</p>
               <p>A thirde cauſe is,<note place="margin">iii.</note> lacke of knowledge of the antiquitie: which ofte cauſeth great hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſeing it is not for euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to knowe the antiquitie: but
<pb facs="tcp:18399:23"/> only for them which be of great ſtudie, wiſedome, and learning in ſundrie authours.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">iiii.</note>A fourth cauſe, that ofte one name is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to diuerſe: yea, &amp; oft one hath diuerſe names.</p>
               <p>A fifth cauſe, that one word oft doeth ſignifie diuerſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges:<note place="margin">v.</note> or that one worde is ofte diuerſllye taken: as this worde <hi>lex,</hi> the lawe, is taken in one place for the figures and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies:<note place="margin">Math. xi.</note> in another for the threateninge of the lawe: in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother for the wholle Byble:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom. iiii.</hi> Hec Orig. lib iii. in Ro. iii. in medio et in eccl. Eraſ. lib. iiii.</note> in another for thold teſtament: in another for the lawe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture before the fal, &amp; in another after the fall: in another for the lawe wrytten: and in another for the lawe of the ghoſpel.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18399:23"/>
               <p>A ſixt cauſe, that repugnance ofte apperith in ſcripture:<note place="margin">vj.</note> as I and my father bee one, my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is gretter then I:<note place="margin">Iohn .x. and .xiiii. Rom. iii. Iames .ii. Epheſ. iiii. Pſalm. iiii. Math. v.</note> we iudge man to be iuſtified by faith with out the workes of the law, man is iuſtified by the workes of the law, and not by fayth only: be angry and offend not, euery one that is angry is worthy Iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment: be angry and offend not, let all indignation and anger be taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you:<note place="margin">Iohn .xiiii. mathew .x. mat. xxviii.</note> I leaue my peace with you, I came not to brynge peace but the ſworde: goe not to the heathen, goe in to all places of the worlde: with ſuche lyke many hundreth places.</p>
               <p>A ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th cauſe,<note place="margin">vij.</note> that one thing in ſcripture is oft diuerſly told, as Stephans reherſal, Actes the vii. is not recited ſtreight as
<pb facs="tcp:18399:24"/> it is in the Geneſis. And ſaint Luke Actes the ix. ſpeakyng of Paules co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion telleth it not as Paule doth him ſelfe, Actes the xxii. and xxvi.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">viij.</note>The eight cauſe, that textes in the newe teſtament are recited furth of the olde, and not worde by worde:<note place="margin">Math. ii</note> as that of Matthew <hi>quoniam Nazereus vocabitur,</hi> He ſhall be called a Nazarite. Yea &amp; ſomtymes fourth of the new and yet not ſo to be founde: as that of the Actes: Chriſt ſayde <hi>beatius eſt dare <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>quam</ex>
                     </expan> accipere.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Actes. xx.</note> It is more bleſſed to geue than to receyue.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">ix.</note>The .ix. cauſe, that ofte ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth variaunce in the yeares and tymes, yea and that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſytie of the tymes oft to them that be well lerned cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb facs="tcp:18399:24"/> great confuſion.</p>
               <p>The .x. cauſe, that textes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tymes which ought ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to be vnderſtand,<note place="margin">x.</note> they take carnally, and lyke wyſe take the contrarie.</p>
               <p>The .xj.<note place="margin">xj.</note> cauſe, that ſomty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes it appereth to the ſenſuall man not to be poſſible: as <hi>Opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet vos naſci denuo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn .iii.</note> Ye muſte bee borne agayne: <hi>Niſi efficiamini ſicut paruuli, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">mat. xxviii<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> Excepte ye be made lyke chylderne. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The .xij. cauſe, that ofte it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth blynd and no profyt in it: as that of the Iudges:<note place="margin">xij.</note> the trees went fourth to anoynt theym a kynge: yea and that of Deut. (Yf. S. Paule had not expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it) thou ſhalte not muſſell the Oxe that treadyh fourth the corne.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18399:25"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">xiij.</note>The .xiij. cauſe, that ofte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſpeketh is not euer well marked. As<note n="†" place="margin">Paul. loquu tus eſt in perſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na imperfecti hoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s:</note> 
                  <hi>non quod volo bonum hoc ago. &amp;c,</hi> The good that I woulde, doe I not: but the euyll whiche I would not, that doe I.<note n="†" place="margin">Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus Ioquitur in Matheo ſub perſona vulga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ris Iudaei.</note> 
                  <hi>Non eſt bonum, ſumere panem filiorum et mittere canibus.</hi> It is not mete to take the chylderns bread and to caſt it to dogges.<note n="†" place="margin">Et in pſa. loquitur ſub perſona cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poris ſui myſtici <hi>Roma. vii. Math. xv. Pſal. xx. Pſal lxviii</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Longe a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute mea verba delictorum meoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> The wordes of myne offenſes are farre from myne healthe. <hi>Delicta mea a te non ſunt abſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita:</hi> Myne offenſes are not hyd from the. &amp;c. Yea &amp; beſyde this ofte in the Pſalmes, in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, in the goſpels, &amp; other places moo alſo very harde (to the knowledge wherof the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerned by theym ſelfes can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:18399:25"/> attayne) the wordes be ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme ſpoken as in perſon of the Prophet hym ſelfe, ſomtyme in perſon of God, ſomtyme of the aungell, ſomtyme of the Deuyl, ſomtyme of man, ſometyme of Chriſte as God, ſometyme of Chriſte as man, ſometyme as head of the church militant, ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme as head of the church tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant, ſomtime as in the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon of his ſenſual parties of his owne body, and ſomtyme in the perſon of ſome particular parte of his body miſticall. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The .xiiii. cauſe, that ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ofte vſeth this terme <hi>all,</hi> where as ſome or parte be but ment. <hi>Cum exaltatus fuero a terra omnia traham. &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. xii<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> When I am lyfte vp from the earth, I wyll drawe all men vnto me. <hi>Omnes</hi>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18399:26"/> loue. &amp;c. beſyde that which lyeth hydde within?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">xix.</note>The .xix. cauſe, that they marke not (and in dede it is not for euery man to marke) what thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges were geuen but for a tyme to continew, and what for euer: As the workynge of myracles was gyuen but for a tyme,<note place="margin">mar. xvi.</note> as S. Augu. in his dayes dyd wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe ſayeng: he that then wold, loke for a myracle was a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle to the worlde hym ſelfe. And that of the actes,<note place="margin">Actes. xv.</note> to abſteyne from that was offred to Idols, to abſteyn from blood, and from ſtraungled.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">xx.</note>The .xx. cauſe, that ſcripture is full of diuerſe and ſoundry ſenſes. It is the boke wrytten (as it is in the Apocalyps) both within and without, in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb facs="tcp:18399:26"/> and in the lettre: within by the ſpiritual meanyng, without by the ſenſe of the letter: within, bycauſe it promiſeth inuiſible thynges, without, for that it diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſeth the viſible thinges: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, bycauſe it moueth to deſire heuenly thynges, without, for that it teacheth worldly thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to be contemned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The .iiii, Chapter,</hi> The letter doeth kyll and that ſondry wayes.</head>
               <p>SEing the letter doth kyl (as. S. Paule ſaith) and that diuerſe wayes, the ignoraunt people ought to be ſore aferde to couet after that whiche cauſeth preſent death.
<pb facs="tcp:18399:27"/> How be it ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s nature is ſuch euer to deſyre that which is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byd.<note place="margin">Nitimur in vetitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per, cupimus<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>egata.</note> Neuertheles for as muche as the letter doth kyll, and that ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry waies, and that the rude ſimple and vnlerned (yea ofty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes the proude, arrogant, and captious) be euer redy to take rather that whiche ſhall hurte then that which ſhall helpe, ſhal the ſcripture then be ſo lefte, that the leuyng of it may be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of ſpirituall death to the multitude?? God forbyde: It ought in no wyſe to be ſuffered.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">j.</note>The letter euer doth kylle when a myſtery is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande (and yet not of the rude to be piked fourth, and therfore not to be had in Engliſh) where the reders wyl ſticke ſtyll to the bare wordes, as the Iewes dyd
<pb facs="tcp:18399:27"/> being prohibited to plow with oxe and aſſe together (whiche was ment, that Iudaiſme and Chriſtianiſme could not be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in one, nor that a chriſtian could ſerue both God and the world) And as ſome haue done in the goſpell (ſaith. S. Augu.) with theſe textes:<note place="margin">Luc. xxii.</note> Selle youre coote and bye a ſworde. &amp;c. I neither receyued nor lerned the goſpell of man (<note place="margin">Galath. i.</note>denyeng therby Chriſt to be man) And as the Anabaptiſtes play with that of Mathew:<note place="margin">mathew. v.</note> thou ſhalt not ſweare at all, with many textes in lyke maner wraſted.</p>
               <p>The letter doth kylle in all places,<note place="margin">ij.</note> where as the holy ghoſt did meane a myſtery after any facion, and yet the reader wyll nat take it. (Yea ofte he can not
<pb facs="tcp:18399:28"/> take it, and therfore not mete to be Iudge in the matter ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng it in englyſh) after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Iewes, which ſtyll ſeke at the letter in theſe textes: the Adder and Dragon thou ſhalt treade vnder thy feete.<note place="margin">Pſalm. c.</note> &amp;c. The wolfe and the lambe ſhall feede together.<note place="margin">Eſay. xi.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Eleuabitur mons domus domini ſuper omnes colles.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſaye. ii. Eſay. ix. Pſal. xx.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c, &amp; ſedebit ſuper ſolium Dauid. &amp;c. Et ponet ſuper caput eius corona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de lapide precioſo, &amp;c,</hi> The hylle where the houſe of God ſhalbe buylded ſhalbe exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted aboue all hilles. &amp;c. He ſhall ſyt vpon the ſeate of Dauid. &amp;c He ſhall ſet a crowne of golde and precious ſtones vppon his head. &amp;c. where as theſe textes and many moo were only to be vnderſtande of Chriſte and of
<pb facs="tcp:18399:28"/> his commyng, though they did not ſo appeare then, nor yet doe to the carnall.</p>
               <p>The letter doeth kyll,<note place="margin">iiij.</note> as ofte as the ſcripture meaneth any other thynge then the wordes doe ſounde as <hi>Comediie amici mei &amp; inebriamini, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. v. Hierm. xxv</note> 
                  <hi>inebria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini &amp; vomite, &amp;c.</hi> Eate my frendes and be dronkene. &amp;c. Dryncke and be dronken, ſpewe and fall. &amp;c. And that of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, when thou haſt a blowe on the one cheke, turne the other:<note place="margin">Math. v.</note> which neither Chriſt nor Paule dyd fulfyll,<note place="margin">Iohn. xvii. Actes. xxiv.</note> as appereth in the goſpell and in thaucters. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore it is Hyperbole diſſwading from reuengement.</p>
               <p>The letter doeth kyl yf time be not obſerued as appeareth in the ſacrifices, figures,<note place="margin">iiij.</note> and
<pb facs="tcp:18399:29"/> prophecies. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">v.</note>The letter doeth kylle the Iewe, which yet doeth affirme the obſeruation of the law.</p>
               <p>The letter doeth kyll the Iewe which doeth ſticke onlye to the letter of the law,<note place="margin">vi.</note> and wil not know that all was writen for vs,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. xv. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor. x.</note> and that all chaunced to them in figure, but wyll ſtycke ſtyll to theyr ſacrifice, circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, choyſe of meates, cleane and vncleane. &amp;c, And wyll not fynde fourth Chriſt there.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">vii.</note>The letter ofte doeth kylle where men take examples to fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low, that be not to be folowed, but rather to be merueld at: as Phinces a priuate perſon pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in ſcripture for manſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:<note place="margin">Num. xxv.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Dan. xiii.</note> Daniel a priuate perſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended the Iudges: And
<pb facs="tcp:18399:29"/> Samuel dyd kyl Agag:<note place="margin">i. Reg. xv. Iud. xvi.</note> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of holy Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred in Cathalogo ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum) for kyllynge hymſelfe: and ſo lykewyſe of theim which woulde goe kyll theymſelfes willingly, bicauſe Chriſt ſaid: he that loſeth his lyfe ſhall ſaue it.</p>
               <p>Be all our Englyſh readers ſo diſcrete that none of theym play as mad partes as theſe, taking occaſion at their engliſh bible? Haue not we as euyll now (though not wholly in the ſame hereſies) as euer were from the begynnyng: eyther Si<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon magus, Martion, Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus, Cherinthus, Cherdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mogenes, Montanus, Tatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Porphyrius, Nouatus, Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rius, Aetius, Eunomius, Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus, Donatus. Manicheus,
<pb facs="tcp:18399:30"/> Pelagius, Wyclyffe, Huſſe, Swynglius, Oecolampadius, or Luther? Yes truly. But eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as at all tymes God hath ſent catholyke Fathers to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe theym, ſo doeth he now in our dayes. Prayſed therfore and glorified be his name for euer and euer, whiche after he had greuouſly ſcourged vs with errours and hereſies a long ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon and many yeares, fyrſt ſent Marye our bleſſed Quene ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng with her oure moſt godly Kynge Philyp (whoſe reignes together, in ioye, vertue, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Ieſus longe preſerue and proſper) and ſence then by theyr meanes beinge inſpired by the holy ghoſt, hath ſent oure hygh Prelate of noble blood my lord Cardinals grace, Legate from
<pb facs="tcp:18399:30"/> the Popes holynes (as for my Lord Chaunceler, my lorde of London, with many other infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, which ſtyll watche and trauell I ſpeake not of) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce vs in to the vnitie, and to brynge vs agayne in to Noes ſhyp, which haue lyen a greate tyme in the maine ſea lyke to be drowned and almoſt in diſpaire of recouerie into the ſhip again.</p>
               <p>The letter doeth kylle all theym that flee from the letter to imaginacion of theyr owne where the letter muſt nedes be taken as it lyeth.<note place="margin">viii.</note> And thus the teſtimonie of the true meanyng of the letter doeth kyll all oure ſacramentaries, whiche denye Chriſtes naturall and reall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the ſacrament of the alter, he ſayinge it is the ſame bodye
<pb facs="tcp:18399:31"/> that honge vpon the Croſſe, but they wyll ſet Chriſte to ſchole, and ſay he wolde haue ſayde, it had ben but a figure. &amp;c. Hath not the engliſh Bible broughte many to this hereſie? both ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that haue ben burnt, and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny mo yet alyue in theyr bodies but deade in theyr ſoules? Was not Ione of Kent thus kylled with the letter, phantaſtically fleyng from it, and not takyng <hi>Verbum caro factum eſt:</hi> arygbt? But denyeng therby Chriſtes trew humanitie? Alſo dyd not the letter thus kyl the late Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian (co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uinced by a lerned yong man named maiſter Proctour) which fondly fled from the trew letter: <hi>Ego &amp; Pater vnum ſumus,</hi> I and my father are both one? So that betwene hym and
<pb facs="tcp:18399:31"/> Ione of Kent Chriſt ſhoulde be nothynge, neyther very God, nor very man,</p>
               <p>The letter doth kylle the fleſhly libertines,<note place="margin">ix.</note> which gather that the Goſpell is ſo free, that they may doe what they wyll: Where as in dede nowe in the new lawe leſſe libertie is geuen to ſynne: and the more perfyte the goſpell is, the more harde it is: and it is not lyght to the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall man, but to hym whiche through charytie and a lyuely fayth, wyllyngly doth all that the law commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, aſcribing all goodnes euer to God.</p>
               <p>The letter doth kyll all ſuche as only doe ſtycke to the gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall ſenſe (<note place="margin">x.</note>which Paule cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth the letter) wher thei ought to ſeke a myſtery.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18399:32"/>
               <p>And thus the letter doeth kyll a ſecte of heretikes <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alled <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropomorphitae,</hi> whyche rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge in the Geneſis, that God ſayde,<note place="margin">Geue. i.</note> let vs make man to our owne image: &amp; readyng alſo in ſundrie places bodily membres attribute to God, doe boldelye ſaye that the Godhead is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall: Readynge alſo that he ſayde.<note place="margin">Gene. v.</note> 
                  <hi>Paenitet me feciſſe homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi> It repenteth me that I made man, aſcribed to hym mans affections: and readyng that he ſayde. <hi>Deſcendam et vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debo.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gene. viii.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I wyll go downe and ſee, &amp;c. Did impute ignoraunce vnto him. Likewiſe it kylleth the ſecte of <hi>Euchitas,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuallye vſe to praye wyth mouthe,<note place="margin">i. Thei. v. Luke. xiiii.</note> becauſe Chriſte and Paule bad praye ſtyll. And it
<pb facs="tcp:18399:32"/> killeth thus another ſorte, that cutte and mangle them ſelues, readinge in the ghoſpell,<note place="margin">Mat. xviii. Coll. iii. Math. xix.</note> plucke out thine eye, cut of thine hand, mortifie your membres vpon the earth. &amp;c. Bleſſed is he that geldeth him ſelfe. &amp;c.<note place="margin">Luc. xiiii. Rom. xii. Math. iii.</note> And an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ſort the letter here doeth kyl, he that hateth not father &amp; mother. &amp;c. Caſte hote coles on your enemies head. &amp;c. He ſhall baptiſe you with the holy ghoſt and fyre. Yea and thus it kylleth the Phariſees which ſuperſtici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly doe wryte the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes in the he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of their garmentes,<note place="margin">Deut. vi.</note> in ſcrolles on po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes. &amp;c. bycauſe God bad kepe them in theyr heartes, and talke of theym euenynge and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng. &amp;c, they dyd not marke that God ment nothyng els by
<pb facs="tcp:18399:33"/> that phraſe of ſpeaking, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a vehement ſtudie and deſire to obſerue the law. Haue not our Englyſhe men (namely in the citie of London) had now of late lyke Iewiſh affection in ſettynge vp wrytynges on the Churche walles and pyllers, euer falſely wraſting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> awrie and applyeng theym to an euyll purpoſe? And thus they painted vp the textes of the new teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon theyr walles: which onely doo ſerue agaynſte the Iewyſhe faſtes to blynde and deceiue the ſymple ſorte there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, as though they had ben ſpoken againſt our holy Vigils and faſtinges. Theſe textes I meane &amp; ſuch like:<note place="margin">Mat. xv.</note> That which entreth in to the mouthe doeth not defile &amp;c Bie al that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth<note place="margin">i. Corin. x.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18399:33"/> into the ſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bles. &amp;c.<note place="margin">Tit. i.</note> All thinges be cleane vnto theym that be cleane, &amp;c. Ye that doe not eate miſiudge not them which eate:<note place="margin">Rom. xiiii.</note> with many moe. And likewiſe they ſette vp theyr textes wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedlie applied both againſt the bleſſed Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Altar and other holye ſacramentes, and alſo againſt oure holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pope. Of ſuche dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable applications of ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res many churches were full. But I would haue wiſhed that in ſtede of theſe they wold haue ſet vp that of, ſ. Peter: my dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued brother Paul,<note place="margin">ii. Pet. iii.</note> wrote many thinges heard which. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The letter doeth kyll beyng red and not trewly vnderſtand,<note place="margin">xj.</note> or trewelye vnderſtande and not obſerued.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18399:34"/>
               <p>The letter is counted to kyl for that it forbyddeth ſynne,<note place="margin">xij.</note> and by occaſion therof augmen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth the deſyre, or els for that it is a witnes againſt vs.</p>
               <p>The letter doeth kylle,<note place="margin">xiii.</note> for that it diſcloſeth oure ſynne: <hi>Concupiſcentiam neſcirem eſſe peccatum &amp;c,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. vii.</note> I had not knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that concupiſcence or luſt had ben ſynne, if the lawe had not ſaide, thou ſhalt not couet or luſte, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">xiiii.</note>The letter doeth kyll as ofte as ye take or applie any texte contrary to the trew meaning of the holy ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">xv.</note>Finally the letter doth kyll all theym that ſearche aboue theyr reache in Gods myſteries (as I feare many haue done in theſe yeares paſt)<note place="margin">Luc. ix.</note> one deſyred to
<pb facs="tcp:18399:34"/> folowe Chriſte, and was not permitted:<note place="margin">Math. viii</note> Another commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to folowe and yet not deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng:<note place="margin">Actes. ix.</note> Yea and Paule greatlye reſiſting was drawen in maner by compulſion. <hi>Conſilia dei oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culta:</hi> gods counſels are vnſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chable. But in theſe miſerable yeares now paſt what myſtery is ſo harde that the ignoraunte with the Bible in englyſh durſt not ſet vppon, yea and ſay they vnderſtod it, all was but lyght? They deſyred no declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but theyr owne euyn in the, hygheſt myſteries: wher as the prophet teacheth that the declaryng or expoundynge of Gods worde doeth gyue lyghte and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to the yonglynges and ignoraunt:<note place="margin">Declaratio ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuorum illuminat et intellectu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dat paruulis.</note> And God thretneth that <hi>(P<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ou. xxv) Scrutator maieſta
<pb facs="tcp:18399:35"/> tis opprimetur a gloria:</hi> theſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher to hyghe in his myſteries ſhalbe thruſt frome his glorie: whiche thinge cauſeth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to ſay:<note place="margin">Pſal. cxxx.</note> 
                  <hi>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ambulaui in magnis, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in mirabilibus ſuper me:</hi> I haue not walked to hygh in great myſteries nor wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders aboue my reache. But alas ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience doeth ſhowe that oure men through hauyng the Bible in engliſſhe haue walked farre aboue theyr reache, beyng ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry wayes kyld &amp; vtterly poiſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the letter of thenglyſh Bible. Therfor for Ieſus ſake away with it, let it kyll no moo,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The. v<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chaptre,</hi> The beſt meanes to vnderſtand the Scriptures by.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:18399:35"/>
               <p>BYcauſe there is ſuch great difficulty and hardnes in Scripture, and bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letter doeth kill many wayes, I thinke nothing can be told more nedefull then to ſhewe playnlye howe we maye beſt come to the trew knowledge of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And therfore here note wel that ſundry and diuerſe thinges be required to obteyne the trew vnderſtanding and meaninge of Scripture by.</p>
               <p>One is, by diſcrete and godly conferrynge place to place,<note place="margin">j.</note> and Scripture to Scripture. And this affirmeth S. Aug. ſayinge,<note place="margin">Aug. lib. iii. de doct. cap. xxvi.</note> the beſte interpretation is to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde one place of Scripture by an other more manifeſt.</p>
               <p>An other is, by conſideringe the time, the men,<note place="margin">ij.</note> with other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances,
<pb facs="tcp:18399:36"/> as how, where, and when they were written.</p>
               <p>An other is, by ſearchinge di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently the proceſſe both before and after.<note place="margin">iij.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">iiij.</note>An other is, by dayly exerciſe ſearching, and aſkinge the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and iudgement of other lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned men.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">v.</note>An other is, by feruent pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and pure deuotion with an humble heart and ſimple ſpirite knowinge that GOD withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the proude,<note place="margin">Iohn. iiii.</note> and alſo that conninge makethe to ſwell in arrogancy,<note place="margin">i. Cor. viii.</note> yf grace be wanting. Wherefore Origen ſayeth that bothe great ſtudye and feruente Praiour be requyred to obteyne the trew intellection of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by.<note place="margin">Homil. xii. in xxxiiii. Exod.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Qu. lxxxxv. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oui et Vet. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſta.</note> And S. Aug. witneſſeth that the holy ſpyrite openeth the
<pb facs="tcp:18399:36"/> meaninge of Scripture onlye to the ſtudious, diligent, &amp; deuoute,<note place="margin">prius amemus ſacras literas qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſcamus, Ia<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> certo per ſu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſum habe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amus in illis nil eſſe ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> falſum n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue. aut huma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na mente ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum: ſed om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia plena caeleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis Philoſophiae digna<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſancto ſpirituquacu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſpecie ſeſe offe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant, ſi vt opor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tet tutelligan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur. haec Aug. de vtili. cred. capi. vi,</note> &amp; deuoute, and to ſuche as haue a firme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefe in the articles of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like faythe receyued. vj.</p>
               <p>And an other is, by ouerſeing the olde and aunciente wryters Iudgementes vpon Scripture, and by conferring theyr expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions together.</p>
               <p>Hereby plainly appereth that with the Engliſhe Bible alone (though it were trewly tranſla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted) man coulde not be brought fully into the trew meaninge of Gods word. But we ſe and wel perceyue, that thouſandes haue ben brought from the trew mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of goddes worde throughe the Engliſhe Byble: therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye with it. It hathe kilde to many ſoules alredy, GOD beſt
<pb facs="tcp:18399:37"/> knoweth: whom I beſeche ſende a ſpedy redreſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The .vi. Chapitre.</hi> Scripture ought not to be in the vulgare tonge, that al men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſtraynt may rede it.</head>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>Fyfty probations of this aſſertion, <hi>The firſt Probation.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Neuer heard nor red that GOD would hys people to haue the booke amonge themſelues to towſe or type at their pleaſure. God gaue the booke to Hieremye and bad him rede to the people that whyche he had written.<note place="margin">Hier. xxxvi.</note> 
                     <note place="margin">Eſay. viii.</note> GOD bad Eſai take the Booke to him for the ſame purpoſe: Yea and it was
<pb facs="tcp:18399:37"/> not without great myſterie that God bad Ezechiell fyrſt eate the Booke,<note place="margin">Ezech. iii.</note> and then rede it in thau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of all the people.<note place="margin">Dan. xiii.</note> Agayne Moyſes gaue the booke to the Leuites to kepe and rede to the people:<note place="margin">iiii. Re. xvii</note> and in kinge Ioſaphat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes time the Prieſtes and Leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes did read the booke and teche the people: like as did alſo after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde Elchias the Prieſt &amp; Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pha the Scribe Eſdras did ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry times take the booke &amp; read it to the people,<note place="margin">iiii. Re. xxii. ii. pa. xxxliii. ii. Eſd. viii. and .xiii. iii. Eſd. ix. Bar. i. Hier. xxxvi.</note> they diligentlye hearinge him. And Baruch the Prophet redde the booke to the kinge and to the people, they ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing eare vnto him:<note place="margin">Luc. iiii.</note> Yea &amp; Chriſt our maiſter toke the booke of the Prophet for this cauſe, and red and expounded to the people: his doing herein was for our exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.
<pb facs="tcp:18399:38"/> Wherby we may eaſely lerne that all people ſhould not haue the Scryptures in their owne handlinges at their pleaſure, as they haue had theſe doſen yeres paſt to their vtter ſpirituall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The ſeconde Probation.</head>
                  <p>God ſente Ionas to preache to Niniue:<note place="margin">Ion. i. &amp; iii.</note> he ſente not a booke writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to euery one of the Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites to reade them ſelues. God ſayde by Hieremy (ſpeakynge of the time of the Goſpell) that the time ſhould come he wold write his law in thartes of his people:<note place="margin">Hier. xxxi.</note> So that the writtinge of tholde law in tables of ſtone (ſignifieng the ſtony hartes of the Iewes) is not to be reioyſed at, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted &amp; to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of, knowinge that Scryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:18399:38"/> was only wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſinne, els neuer had ben written, but only in the heart of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It was three thouſande yeres after the creation of the world before the olde lawe was written: and yet then only writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for wickednes and ſynne. It was alſo a longe ſpace after the aſcenſion before the new Teſtament was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ſome parte at one tyme and ſome at an other, and yet euery parte only writen for ſynne and ſciſme: ſo that the ſimple igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt people, this wel conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ought not to be ſo deſyrous of the ſcripture written, as they ought to be deſyrous to heare the trew meanyng of ſcripture: for that onlye is the ſcripture and the goſpell of Chriſte. For ſayth. S. Hierom. <hi>Euangelium
<pb facs="tcp:18399:39"/> non eſt in ſcriptura, ſed in ſenſu: non in ſuperficie, ſed in medulla: non in ſermonum folijs, ſed in ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice rationis.</hi> The goſpell is not in the wryting, but in the ſenſe: it is not in the outwarde appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, but in the inward mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng: it is not in the leaues of the bokes, but in the ghoſtly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandynge. Chriſt neuer bad goe write his goſpell or holye worde, but badde preache it. Then yf thou haſt an humble heart, and canſt but reade the englyſh Bible, thinke thou muſt haue it taught thee, and not to take it thy ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Saye as the Eunuche dyd to Philip:<note place="margin">Actes. viii.</note> howe can I vnderſtand it except I be taught? Chriſte did preache ofte to the people,<note place="margin">Math. iiii.v</note> but he wrote not to them at all:
<pb facs="tcp:18399:39"/> and he ſent his diſciples and bad them preache to the people his ghoſpel,<note place="margin">Mark .i. Luc. viii. Math. x. and .xxviii. Mar. vi.iii.xvi. Luc. ix.xxiiii Luc. xii.</note> and then they went and preached, but he bad them not write at all. That whiche ye haue hearde (ſayeth he) in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete places ſhalbe preached on the toppes of the houſes: he ſaid not it ſhalbe written in youre churches (as it hathe been Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſhly vſed on late here in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande) nor written in Bybles to be read of euerye one in hys mother tongue, and ſet vp for that purpoſe in euerye churche, Peter ſayeth the holye fathers did ſpeake Gods worde by the holye ghoſt:<note place="margin">ii. Pet. i.</note> he telleth nothinge of writyng it.<note place="margin">Math. xxvi</note> Chriſte where he ſpake of the memorial of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Magdalene, ſaide: wherſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer this ghoſpell ſhalbe prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched.
<pb facs="tcp:18399:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> &amp;c. He ſayde not wherſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer this Ghoſpell ſhalbe writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.<note place="margin">Mark .i. Luc. iii.</note> Iohn Baptiſt preached muche, but where did he either write or commaund to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten?<note place="margin">Mat. xxiiii.</note> Chriſte ofte promiſed that hys Ghoſpell ſhoulde bee preached in all the worlde:<note place="margin">Mar. vi. Luc. x.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>And therfore ſent fourth bothe the apoſtles, and the lxxij. diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and all godly preachers euer ſince (ſo that none canne preache except he be ſent.<note place="margin">Rom. x.</note>) But in no place we rede that he bad go write his ghoſpel. I can not then but meruayl that men to their owne confuſion are ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſierous to haue the ſcripture in their mother tongue. O howe oft ſpeaketh Paule, and S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter alſo of preachinge the ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell?<note place="margin">Rom. x.xv.</note> In the Epiſtle to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes,
<pb facs="tcp:18399:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> in either Epiſtle to the Corinthians,<note place="margin">i. cor. ix.xv: ii. Cor. i.xi. Gal. i.iiii.v. Epheſ. ii. Phillip. i. Col. i. i. Theſ. ii. i. Tim. ii.iii. ii. Tim. iiii. Act. ix.xv.xx i. Pet. iii, iiii Act. vix.xv. Luc. x. Math. vii. Luc. xi. Actes. x. Actes. xix.</note> to the Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to the Epheſians, to the Philippians, to the Coloſſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, to the Theſſalonians, to Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothe, and in Thartes. And S. Peter alſo bothe in his firſt Epiſtle &amp; alſo thriſe in thactes Beſides this, Martha is pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Ghoſpell for hearyng Chriſtes worde taughte: and Chriſt in his ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſaieth, he that heareth my word and doeth it (not he that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it or writeth it) ſhalbe like ned to the wiſe man buildynge vpon the rocke. &amp;c. And agayne bleſſed be they that heare gods worde and kepe it: and as it is in the Actes when Peter prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, the holy ghoſt fell vpon al that heard him: yea and they of
<pb facs="tcp:18399:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> Aſia were praiſed for hearynge Gods word. But wher (I pray you) haue you of writynge it for all men to read? Howe be it the onelye drifte (as I thynke) of all ſuche as obſtinatly ſticke to haue the ſcripture in writing in the vulgar tongue, is therby to be Iudges of the ſenſe of ſcripture them ſelues, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to the vniuerſall churche of Chriſt. But therfore it may not be ſuffered.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The thirde probation.</head>
                  <p>THrough the damnable libertie of hauinge it in the vulgar tongue haue not all holye myſteries been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed? Haue they not therby vt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terly condemned all that hathe
<pb facs="tcp:18399:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> not been expreſſed in the letter of their Engliſhe Byble? Haue they not made vs worſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by then the Iewes? To take all myſteries from vs excepte they be expreſſed in their Engliſhe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Iewes durſt not expreſſe the highe name of God <hi>Iehoua,</hi> But what myſterie durſte not our men medle withal? Yea rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, turne &amp; toſſe at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? The Iewes had <hi>Cabala</hi> their tradition left among them by Moyſes without writynge, receyued as it were by hande from generation to generation, concernynge the myſticall ſenſe included in the wordes of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: But through this damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hereſye our men haue whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye condemned all that is not expreſſed in the letter of theyr
<pb facs="tcp:18399:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> Engliſhe. And yet S. Iohn ſayde, I had manye thinges to write vnto you, neuertheleſſe, I woulde not write with paper and ynke, but I truſte to come and ſpeake with you mouthe to mouth:<note place="margin">Aug. ad Ianu.</note> yea and S. Auguſtine ſayeth: <hi>quae non ſunt ſcripta ſed tradita cuſtodimus, quae to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to terrarum orbe obſeruantur:</hi> we kepe and obſerue not only ſuch thinges as be written, but alſo traditions not written, whiche be obſerued in all places of chriſtendome. Agayne, yf ye wil nothinge to be Gods word but that whiche is expreſſed in the letter written, what ſay ye then to Moyſes? Were not the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of God ſpoken to him gods worde tyll they were written? Wer not the wordes of God ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:18399:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> to the Apoſtles gods word tyl they were written? Chriſt in ſayinge to Peter bleſſed arte thou &amp;c,<note place="margin">Mat. xvi.</note> declareth that that high myſtery came into S. Peters heart) as to the prince of Chap poſtles) onelye by ſecret inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and not by the worde written. And ſo doeth lykewiſe this, that neyther Euangeliſt nor Apoſtle did euer by writing ſende the faith to anye nation, but where they were firſte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by preaching. For faith commeth by hearynge (ſayeth Paule) and not by writynge.<note place="margin">Rom. x.</note> Furthermore, Paule bad the Theſſalonians (as I ſayde) kepe the traditions whiche he had geuen them by mouth:<note place="margin">ii. Theſ. ii.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the wordes that he ſpake to the people by mouth, our lord
<pb facs="tcp:18399:43"/> and vſed aboute the ſacrament of the Altar, or about the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of baptiſme, who can ſhew the reaſon fully of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes, geſtures, orders, queſtions, and aunſweres there vſed? And yet all theſe wee haue receiued of Chriſt and his Apoſtles. Thus muche ſayth Origene.</p>
                  <p>And here marke I beſeche you of Origenes woordes (whiche was liui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in lxxxx. yeres after ſaint Iohn the Euangeliſt) that many ſuche traditions were left by Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles, which bee not in the Byble expreſſed, and yet to be obſerued of all faythful Catholike people.</p>
                  <p>Beſide this what they wyl ſaye to manye thinges moe not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in Scripture and yet vnder the payne of damnation
<pb facs="tcp:18399:43"/> to be beleued I cannot tel: as to the Baptim of infantes: the .iii. perſons in Trinitie to be of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall power and of one eſſence, that God the Father is <hi>ingenitꝰ</hi> not begot, the procedinge of the holye goſt from the father &amp; the Sonne: the deity &amp; equalitye of the Holy Goſte with the father and the Sonne: the obſeruynge of the Sonday: the order of our Crede: the continuance of the virginite of our Lady: that ſhe is <hi>Theorocos mater dei,</hi> the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God: the receyuinge the Sacrament of thalter faſting: the mixtinge water with wyne in the Chalice: the Sonne to be conſubſtantial with the father: that Chriſtes ſoule deſcended in to hel: the making of the ſigne of the Croſſe: the numbre of the
<pb facs="tcp:18399:44"/> Sacramentes: that there be .ii. natures in Chriſte knit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>in vnitate diuine ſuppoſite:</hi> &amp; that Soules departinge hens ſtreyght wayes haue the fruitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the deitye: And that men and women haue power to miniſtre the Sacrament of Baptym, It is not expreſſed in ſcripture, ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther by commaundement, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, licence, or example.</p>
                  <p>what they will ſay to this gere, I wot not: but this one thynge I am wel aſſured of, that haui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Scripture in Engliſhe hath brought tholy myſteries of God into contempte and hatred.</p>
                  <p>Where as the wiſedome of God (as S.<note place="margin">Baſil. deſpiritu ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cto. cap. xxvij.</note> Baſill teſtifieth) neuer wolde all the miſteries of our faith to be put in writing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="tcp:18399:44"/> to be a laughinge ſtocke both to the Iewes and Gentils. For if Chriſte himſelfe were counted a ſclaunder to the Iewes, and foliſhnes to the Heathens, how muche rather ſhal the high my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of our fayth ſo be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted being moſt harde to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued?<note n="†" place="margin">Myſterium no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt quod ad po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulares aures effertur. patr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s ergo in occu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>to ac ſilentio miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terijs ſuam ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauere digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Baſi. xxvii de ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſancto.</note> Agayne it is not a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery (ſayeth he) that is open to euery man, or that is blowen in to euery mans eare. Tholy Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers euer kept tholy miſteryes in moſt ſecrecy reuerencyng the dignitie therof. S. Dioniſe,<note place="margin">Dioni. cap. i. in celeſ. hierarch. Iren. lib. <hi>3.</hi> ca <hi>4</hi> Epiphan. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Aeriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Tertul de cor. mili. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig. homil. v, in num. Cypri. de Lot, pedu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Hila in pſal, ij.</note> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reneus, Epiphanius, Tertulia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Origen, Ciprian, and Hylari with one conſent do firmelye e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſſhe this agaynſte the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouers of thengliſſhe tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions: Yea and S. Baſill dothe
<pb facs="tcp:18399:45"/> affirme that there be ſo manye myſteries without Scripture whiche muſt be credited, that he can in no ſmall time recite them al: <hi>Deficier me dies (inquit) ſi eccle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiae myſtria citra ſcriptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tradita per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gam recenſere.</hi> Howe can it then be that the Engliſſhe Bible can continue, many ſuch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taking occaſion thereby to condemne al holy myſteries receiued by the Catholyke Churche euen from the begynninge, S. Iohn teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge that ſo many moe thinges wer done, that the whole world were not hable to conteme all if they were wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? And ſ. Paule bidding the Theſſalonians (as ye haue hearde) obſerue all his tradicions, receyued by mouthe, &amp; not by writyng (ſayeth Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philact) and yet aſwel to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued
<pb facs="tcp:18399:45"/> as thother? Yea and in the time of ſ. Peter, Linus, Cletus, Anacletus, Clement &amp; Euariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. &amp;c. S. Iohns Goſpell was not written: but theſe men wyll nothing to be beleued but onlye that whiche is in their Engliſhe Byble: ſo that all that time the Chriſtians by this their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould not haue ben bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to beleue that whiche is now in S. Iohns Goſpel, bycauſe then it was not written. Howe be it al faythfull people beleue that the Churche of Chriſte taught aboue .lx. yeres after Chriſtes aſcenſion all that is now in S. Iohns Goſpell, beinge yet not then written. In the time our mother the Churche was a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin. I meane not corrupt nor adulterate with ſundry hereſies
<pb facs="tcp:18399:46"/> there were almoſt no ſcriptures of the new Teſtament in Paper and Inke.</p>
                  <p>All the monitions, wordes, and workes of Chriſte were then writen in the hertes of the faythfull: but ſone after when through ſynne it bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to wax colde, then was writing for the ſimples ſake to preſerue theyr faith: and yet that not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding the authorite of the church (the fundacion of all treuth) of as greate ſtrenght as it was before the new teſtament was all writen. For were there not heretikes (I pray you) which denyed diuerſe bokes of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as Martion and other? wherewith were they ſubdued? euyn with verities not written, Marke wel that Moyſes (ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:18399:46"/> Origene) greatly paſſed not for the letter writen when he dyd breake the tables: nor Chriſte when he ſayd to the Iewes, the ſcripture ſhalbe take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from you, ſpake of the letter (whiche they kepe ſtyl) but of the ſenſe. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore awaye with the engliſhe damnable tranſlation and lette them lerne the myſteries of god reuerently by hert: and lerne to geue as muche credit to that whiche is not expreſſed, as to that which is expreſſed in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: Knowing that in .iij. poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes thautoritie of the churche is aboue the aucthoritie of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. One is in fortifieng veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties not writen to be neceſſary to ſaluation (as plainly appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by manye verities in this probation) another is for that
<pb facs="tcp:18399:47"/> the church receyued the goſpels of Luke and Marke (whiche Marke neuer ſaw Chriſt) and did reiecte the Goſpels made by his high Apoſtels, Thomas and Bartilmew: as for the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Nicodeme (which yet was familiar with Chriſte) I ſpeake not of. The thyrde is, bycauſe the church in all doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cauſes and matters of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie muſt euer be iudge of the trew ſenſe of ſcripture. For ſhe alone hath euer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe of ſcripture. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by her authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie onely Ireneus did conuince Vale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tin: Tertulian, Mertion: Origen, Celſum: Ciprian, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatum: Nicen councell, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians: Hierom, Iouinian: and Auguſtine, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Donatiſtes: with many other. And no meruell,
<pb facs="tcp:18399:47"/> for ſo muche Chriſt him ſelfe made his Churche the Iudge ouer ſcripture, when he ſent the Apoſtels &amp; diſciples to preache ſayeng: He that heareth you, heareth me. And alſo when he ſayd: Who ſo would not heare the Churche, ſhould be reputed and taken as an Ethnycke, or Publican. Seyng then that God thus appointed, who wyll refuſe to ſeke the trew vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge of ſcripture at that iudge, whome Chriſt appointed hymſelfe? Surely none but ſelfe willie heretykes.</p>
                  <p>And here nowe to ſpeake a worde or two of the Saboth, and of mixtinge water wyth wine in the chalice (whereof I ſhould haue ſpoken before, when I recited manye verities not written) and firſte concernynge
<pb facs="tcp:18399:48"/> the Saboth. Albeit the matter of the precept be morall and the daye legal, ſo that it myght be chaunged: yet the church would neuer haue done that, without ſpeciall ordinaunce of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge made iudge in the cauſe.</p>
                  <p>And likewiſe it is to be ſayde of mixtinge water wyth wyne in the chalice. The Ghoſpel ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth of wine onely tourned into Chriſtes precious bloude, who durſte then mixte water there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with? But the church is ſo aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of Goddes pleaſure therein without any ſcripture, that they dare not only put in water, but alſo dare not leaue it oute. And wherby knewe the church theſe thinges, but by Chriſte and hys holy Apoſtles whiche taught in their time? And ſo in theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:18399:48"/> and manye other moe went it furth from age to age conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuinge in the churche tyll thys daye, begonne by Chriſt in the beginninge withoute mention made in ſcripture written.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .iiij. probation.</head>
                  <p>Some deſire to haue it in the englyſhe tongue only for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and this is but curioſitie: ſome only for vain praiſe, &amp; this is but vain glory to be ſene lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned: Some only to taunt poore prieſtes and other therewith, and this is but deueliſhnes: ſo that for none of theſe it ought to be in engliſh. Nowe where ſome would deſyre it in engliſh only to be edified thereby (for this deſyre only is to be embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) treuth is they may be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently edified by ſermons and
<pb facs="tcp:18399:49"/> holſom doctrine of the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res expounded vnto theym by ſuch as haue the key of knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as ofte as they ſhall well requyre: and herewith a godly minde wyl be content, knowing that the contrary is againſt the catholyke church. So that euin the good and catholyke people which would doe good and noo hurt with the Bible in engliſh, yet may not be permitted to kepe it in the engliſh to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge: part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leſt the infirme and weake thereby ſhould be offended, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in miſiudging, or in taking example (yf occaſion ſerue) to get the ſame libertie to theyr deſtruction, and partly that no occaſion be geuen therby to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate heretikes to murmur that they haue it not in engliſh
<pb facs="tcp:18399:49"/> them ſelues as wel as thother. And this anſwer I geue vnto theym which ſeme of a godlye zeale to ſay, ſcripture ought to be in engliſh for the vſe and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moditie of ſuch people as with an earneſt zeale and deuoute ſtudy doo hunger and thurſte the ſimple and plaine knowlege of Gods worde, not for conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious bablyng, but for innocent lyuyng, not to be curious ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the high myſteries, but to be faithfull doers of Gods byddyngs: not to be troublous talkers of the Bible, but ſincere folowers of Gods preceptes therin conteyned: not to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuerent reaſoners in holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture for vain ſetti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g out of their painted ſheathe, but to be hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble and louly workers of Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry:
<pb facs="tcp:18399:50"/> not to be curious diſputers in the Goſpell for the maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of theyr inordinate luſtes and carnall libertye, but to be vpryghte walkers in holye conuerſation of lyfe in the rule of the goſpell preſcribed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The fyfte probation.</head>
                  <p>Hauyng the ſcripture in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſh they preſume to know all the ſcriptures perfitly (and that to theyr condemnation) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to .ſ. Hieroms rule which is this, <hi>Si non ſuccedat idoneus interpres, potius neſcire oportet <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>quam</ex>
                        </expan> cum periculo diſcere. &amp;c.</hi> Yf there be not one preſent that is mete to expounde the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, it is better not to know the myſteries, then with ieoperdie
<pb facs="tcp:18399:50"/> and peryll to ſearche theim. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The ſyxte probacion.</head>
                  <p>The moſt parte of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be euyll: but Chriſte wolde none ſuch ſhould haue the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of his ſecrettes: as appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by that he willeth precious ſtones not to be caſte amongeſt ſwine, nor holye breade to dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Therfore ſcripture ought not ſo to be lefte, that all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anye diſcretion or difference may ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle it at their pleaſures: whiche muſte nedes be, if it be ſette at libertie in the vulgar tongue in euerye churche.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The ſeuenth probation.</head>
                  <p>The moſte part of the people be ignoraunt &amp; not hable to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne betwene the letter and the
<pb facs="tcp:18399:51"/> myſtery: but none ſuche be mete iudges in ſuche high matters (&amp; yet none wylbe more bolde then blynde bayarde) therefore the ſcripture muſt be kepte furth of the handling of all ſuche: which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be, if it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in Engliſh as it doth, for all men to diſpute of it that wyll.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The eight probation.</head>
                  <p>Is not the ſcripture ful of fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures and tropes? Shal it then be ſo lefte, that euery one ſhalbe iudge therof?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The ninth probation.</head>
                  <p>The vniuerſal church of Chrſt did neuer allowe nor approue Scripture to bee in the vulgare tongue, weying the manifolde inconueniences, that haue iſſued thereof: but euer from tyme to tyme amonge other errours
<pb facs="tcp:18399:51"/> did tread that doune &amp; ſuppreſſe it. If we therfore, according to the article of oure Crede, beleue the vniuerſal Churche, we muſt not admit the ſcripture to be in our Engliſhe tongue, knowing that as S. Ciprian ſayeth, that whiche hathe been done and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned by the church (the holye ghoſt being the guyde) is of as great weyght, as that whiche was done by Chriſt him ſelfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The tenth probation.</head>
                  <p>Scripture is cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to be ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>times meate, ſomtimes drinke:<note place="margin">Greg. lib. i. moral.</note> drinke in light places, meate in obſcure places, which in expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge is as it were eaten being broken. It was not therefore withoute great myſterie that Chriſt cauſed the Apoſtles to breake the breade to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb facs="tcp:18399:52"/> of the people, whom he fed with v. loaues, ſignifiynge the ſpirituall breakynge of the bread of the ſoule amonge the people euer to bee done by the miniſters diligentlye: and that it ſhould not be complayned vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Prophet,<note place="margin">Hierem. Thren. iiii.</note> ſayinge: my children haue deſired bread, and there was none to breake it to them: and likewiſe by Amos: there is a great hunger (ſayeth he) not of lacke of bodily foode, but of hearinge the worde of God. And alſo by Eſay, the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles did periſh for lacke of mete and the multitude for lacke of drinke.<note place="margin">Eſay. v.</note> By theſe it maye well appeare that the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhoulde not preſume to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, nor to be iudges therof: whiche
<pb facs="tcp:18399:52"/> yet they wyll doe (as experience ſheweth) yf they haue it in the vulgar tongue. Therfore away with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The eleuenth probation.</head>
                  <p>There be diuers and ſundrie ſenſes in the ſcripture (as bothe Origen and Auguſtine doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare) whiche be not for euerye ſimple brayne to finde out.<note place="margin">Orig. homil. <hi>2.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>11.</hi> in Ge. Aug. de vtilitate cre. ad honor. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> The myſterie oft is hidde, the well of ſcripture is depe, <hi>puteus altus eſt:</hi> euery ones ſtrength is not hable to drawe vp the water of lyfe furth of the botome of it. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the welle muſte be couered, leſt the yonglinges fall into it, and ſo be drowned.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The xii. probation.</head>
                  <p>Paule thought not the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians hable to haue the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries opened vnto them,<note place="margin">i. Cor. iii.</note> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:
<pb facs="tcp:18399:53"/> I feede you with milke, &amp; yet our moſt ignorant people wyll murmur, if they may not fede the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues with the higheſt myſteries of all, euen in theyr owne natiue language. Paule ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th he fedde the Corinthians as younge children, whiche yf they fede the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues wyl defile &amp; ſlober their clothes. And do not theſe nowe in oure dayes defile theyr weddinge garmente with preſuming to feede them ſelues with ſpiritual fode of the ſoule? And marke here I prai you that it was not without cauſe that Paul vſed here this ſimilitude, ſeinge children not ſuffered to fede them ſelues ofte ſtrike the meate (throughe frowardnes) furth of the nources hande, ofte forſake it, and tourne awaye: euen as doe ſtyl the wicked whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:18399:53"/> woulde feede them ſelues ſpirituallye with the engliſhe tranſlation of ſcripture to theyr vtter poyſoning after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of children, which being per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted to fede them ſelues, may gather vp poyſon or ven<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m, and fede thereon: not that I meane that in ſcripture ſhoulde be any poyſon: but that a medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine miniſtred by the Phiſitian oft healeth, which take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by your ſelfe not knowinge how, where nor when to take it, poyſoneth and kylleth. The Bee and the Spider gather on one floure, the one honye, the other poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: the floure miniſtring no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion thervnto, but onely their owne natures. Where vpon S. Auguſtine ſayeth:<note place="margin">Aug. in pſal. xlviij.</note> 
                     <hi>omnia diuina eloquia ſalubria ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bene intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus:
<pb facs="tcp:18399:54"/> periculoſa ijs qui eam volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ad ſui cordis peruerſitatem detor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere:</hi> all holye ſcriptures be holſome and moſte profitable to them that vnderſtande them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right: but they be perilous to al ſuche whiche wyll wraſt them after the frowardneſſe of theyr owne heartes. O lorde howe manye haue wraſted the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture amiſſe throughe the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked libertie of hauinge it in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe theſe many yeares?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The xiii. probation.</head>
                  <p>Chriſt ſayd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Saduces, ye do erre not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math. xxii.</hi> Ioſeph. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de bel. Iud. et. li. <hi>18.</hi> de antiquit.</note> &amp; the cauſe was, that thei receyued no interpreters vppon ſcripture, not muche vnlike vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our men, which only with the Engliſhe tranſlation (though it be neuer ſo falſe, ſo corrupt, and
<pb facs="tcp:18399:54"/> dampnable) woulde take vpon them the full vnderſtandynge of ſcriptures.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .xiiii. probation,</head>
                  <p>Saincte Peter teſtified (as it is in my fyrſte chapter) that many thynges in. S.<note place="margin">ii. Pet. iii.</note> Paules epiſtles were hard to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, which the vnlearned did then peruert to theyr deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as they dyd other places of ſcriptures. And yet for all this dare our vnlearned men be ſtyll deſyrous to haue the ſame ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures in theyr owne ſpeache to peruerte to theyre owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The ,xv, probation</head>
                  <p>Dyd Chriſt ofte teſtifie that it was not for euery one too knowe the high myſteries, and yet dare the blynde ſo preſume
<pb facs="tcp:18399:55"/> ſtyll onely with theyr Engliſh tranſlation? It was not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out great cauſe that Chriſt woulde not his myſteries to be publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to al people. For the comen ſort neuer vſed them well. And therfore many hyghe myſteries there be (ſayth. S. Baſyl) which neuer were wrtten, but in the heart of the elect. And. S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom vpon, <hi>Labia ſacerdotis cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diunt ſcientiam:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Malach. ii.</note> ſayeth that the miniſters of Chriſtes Churche whoſe duty is to teach the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, muſt not ſtyll vtter, but kepe,<note place="margin">Tertull. in lib. de praeſcript. hae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ret. in medio li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri tribuit om<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nibus apoſtolis arcana cognoſce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, quae ignobili vulgo no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> licuit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> that in tyme and place it may be publiſhed: Theyr office is this to do, &amp; not for euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſearche the ſecretes. Chriſte wold, not euery one to be a med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, when he ſayde to his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: it ſhall be youre office to
<pb facs="tcp:18399:55"/> know the myſteries: and to Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codeme: Art thou a Maſter in Iſraell, and knoweſt not this gere? as who ſhould ſaye, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to teachers to be rype in ſcriptures, and for other to be hearers.<note place="margin">iiii. Eſd. xii.</note> God ſaid to Eſdras ſpeakyng and declaring hygh miſteries: put theſe ſecretes ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely vp, and teache theym to the wiſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be hable to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande theym:<note place="margin">iiii. Eſd. iiii.</note> as for the lewde he rebuketh theym as vnmete to knowe ſuche highe ſecretes and myſteries. Euery Idiote can beare ſtones to the building of a houſe, and lay a hepe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but none can couche theym as they ought to be in theyr pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, but the maſon: euery foole can reade and bable of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, but only the godly learned
<pb facs="tcp:18399:56"/> teachers can play the ſpirituall maſons parte in couchyng the lyuely ſtones in the ſpirituall buylding of Chriſtes houſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .xvi. probation.</head>
                  <p>God ſayth by Malache the prophet (I recited the text euin now) that the people muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre the law and the meaning therof at the mouth of the priſt:<note place="margin">Mala. ii.</note> but then is it not for euery one to take it himſelfe, to controlle &amp; deſcaunt at his own pleaſure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .xvii, probation.</head>
                  <p>Can the vnlearned only with the engliſh bible and with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding only the engliſh tranſlatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſcerne or know how Chriſtes wordes be trewe that he came to fulfylle the lawe,<note place="margin">Math. v.</note> and not to breake it, and how many maner of wayes that is trewe, and yet
<pb facs="tcp:18399:56"/> how he is the ende of the lawe? Agayn can he perceyue therby how the old teſtament and the new are both one in ſubſtaunce,<note place="margin">Vetus lex oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultatio nouae, nona reuelatio veteris, Aug.</note> and yet diuerſe in perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and in imperfection, &amp; what nedeth the olde ſtyll to remayne, yea or what neded the newe to be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſeyng Chriſte anſwered to the lawyer aſkinge howe to come to heauen:<note place="margin">Luc. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> In the lawe what readeſt thou? Loue thy lord God. &amp;c. Moreouer can he ſee in his engliſh booke how the goſpel is eaſy and lyght? (for ſo Chriſt calleth it) and that thold was ouer hard and importable as it is in thactes the .xv. ſeyng that in thold only manſlaughter was forbyd, here to be angry is is condemned: there loue thy frende, here loue thyne enemy:
<pb facs="tcp:18399:57"/> there, eye for eye, here, yf thou haſt a boffet on thone ſide, turne thother: there, commytte no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultery, here, yt thou beholdeſt a woman vnchaſtly thou art an adulterer: there, thou ſhalt not be forſworne, here thou ſhalte not ſweare at al: there, for ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng other mens goodes y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> muſt reſtore fourefold, here, for not geuyng thyne owne thou mayſt be dampned? Can ye with then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh bible tell theſe and many moo as hard thynges as theſe be? I am ſure ye can not. And therfore if ye might be ſuffered (whiche God forbyde) ſtyll to wade in thengliſh tranſlation, ye muſte nedes ſtyl walke from blindnes to blindnes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .xviii. probation.</head>
                  <p>In the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes
<pb facs="tcp:18399:57"/> o how many hard thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined? yea what part of ſcripture is ſo lyghte that a godly learned man dare take in hand fully to diſcuſſe, expound, and declare by his owne witte, yf he doe not ſee nor neuer haue ſene anye doctor or expoſitoure theron? And yet ſhall ſcripture be ſuffered to continew in then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh tongue for all men to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde at theyr pleaſure.?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .xix. probation.</head>
                  <p>What thinges haue we got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the ſcriptures beyng in englyſh theſe yeares paſt? ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes ſtubbourne, frowarde and diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to theyr maſters and maſtres, fleſhly liberty, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tempt of all godly order, loſſe of deuotion and godlynes, prayer and faſtyng ſet at nought, and
<pb facs="tcp:18399:58"/> vnbrydled boldneſſe to all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chefe. See then whether it be high tyme to take it awaye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne. Suffer the ſword of the ſpirit to continew no longer in the mad mans hande.<note place="margin">Hebre. iiii.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .xx. probation.</head>
                  <p>Who is hable to tell at the fyrſt ſight how many hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth fautes be euyn in theyre beſt tranſiation (yf there were any good) and yet ſhall they be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſtyll to continewe? ſhall they ſtyll poyſon moo? lyke as doo a thouſande damnable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſh bokes ſette furth within theſe .xxij. yeares. Lord delyuer vs from theim al, and that with all ſpede. I take God to record (yf I may ſpeake only of one faute in the tranſlation and touche no moo) my herte dyd
<pb facs="tcp:18399:58"/> euer abhorre to here this word <hi>dominus,</hi> (whiche moſt comonly doth include <hi>noſter</hi>) to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the Lorde, where as it ought to be tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated our Lord, the very latyn phraſe ſo decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng: as appeareth ſufficiently by that one exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of the comike where one ſayth to Pamphilus <hi>Pater eſt,</hi> what man that hath a iudgement in the latyn tonge can denie this word <hi>Pater</hi> here in this place to include <hi>tuus,</hi> &amp; ſo to be tranſlated in to Englyſhe thy father? is not the ſame iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement to be geuen of. S. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hans ſayeng to Peter, Iohan the .xxj. <hi>Dominus eſt:</hi> It is oure Lorde our Maiſter: where as they haue falſely tranſlated it, as in many other places, calling him the Lord? And lykewiſe in
<pb facs="tcp:18399:59"/> the ſalutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Lady, Haile Mary full of grace <hi>dominus te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum:</hi> doth not here this worde <hi>dominus</hi> include <hi>noſter?</hi> woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou make tharchaungell lyke a deuyll to calle hym <hi>the lorde?</hi> he is the lord to the deuyl, but to vs he is our moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lorde, and ſo to be called. Our father which art in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> halowed be thy name. &amp;c. And S. Thomas cryed, my Lorde &amp; my God. Agayn, ſeing God is Lorde of Abraham, Lorde of Iſaac, and Lorde of Iacob, would then Abraham, Iſaac, or Iacob call hym the Lord? no trulye: but my Lorde, or oure Lord. This I ſpeake not now ſo much for the tranſlatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſeing it ſwarmeth as full of faultes as leaues (I wil not ſay lines)
<pb facs="tcp:18399:59"/> as I doe for that I would wiſh that the comen ſpeache amonge people (ſpro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of cuſtom through the fond tranſlation) I thanke the Lord, the Lorde be prayſed, the Lorde knoweth, with all ſuche phraſes might be left, and that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people might be taughte to call hym our Lord, I thanke our Lord, our Lord be prayſed, our Lorde knoweth. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The xxi. probation.</head>
                  <p>The holy martyr and chiefe by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe, S. Clement writynge to S. Iames Thapoſtle wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the worde of God not to be read after euerye mans toye in his brayne, ſeinge manye places of ſcripture (ſayeth he) without the leadinge of the holye ghoſt, maye be wraſted and taken af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter euerye mans leude mynde
<pb facs="tcp:18399:60"/> and fonde iudgement (whiche thinge hath been put in practiſe of late) and not as the ſpirite of God dyd meane.<note place="margin">Oportet ab eo intellige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cere ſcriptura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, qui ea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> á ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioribus ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veritatem ſibi tradita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeruat. Haec diuus Cle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mens lib. x. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cog. Idem quo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> doce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Iren. Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull. Athan. et Epiphan.</note> But (ſayeth he) we muſt euer learne the true meaninge of ſcripture of hym whiche doeth obſerue it, as he hath accordinge to trueth recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it of the elders. Hereby we maye perceyue that we muſte e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer take the meanynge of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture at his hande that went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the trueth of Chriſtes vniuerſal church. But how can it then be in the Englyſh tonge, for al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to read &amp; take as they haue done at their pleaſure? thei haue made ſcripture no ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by falſe recitynge, by falſe wraſtyng and tournyng. For as Martiall<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſayeth: <hi>Quem recitas meus eſt o Philentine libellus, At
<pb facs="tcp:18399:60"/> male cum recitas incipit eſſe tuus.</hi> O my frende the boke that thou reciteſt is myne, but when thou makeſt falſe recitall, then thou makeſt it thine owne booke and none of myne. O lorde in howe many places maye ſcriptuce by the wicked be tourned into ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie facions (as God knoweth it hath been) euen after the ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Apollo. <hi>Aio te aeacida Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manos vincere poſſe?</hi> Is it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be continued in thengliſh tonge?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The xxij. probation.</head>
                  <p>If ſcripture in the vulgar tongue had been nedefull, God woulde haue ſent it to the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuche, to Saule, and to Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius in the viij.ix. and x. of thac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: but there ye reade that god ſent them teachers, Philip, Ana<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny, and Peter: and not the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture:
<pb facs="tcp:18399:61"/> whiche hadde been but in vayne as appeareth by the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuches ſayinge: howe ſhall I vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſcripture by reading except I be taught? Whervpon S. Hierom ſayth. <hi>Ego (vt de me loquar) nec ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctior ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hoc eunucho, nec ſtudioſior, qu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> librum tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret &amp;c. ignorabat tamen eum que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in libro neſciens venerabatur.</hi> O howe manye this daye, muche more ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t then Theunuche, will take in hande onelye with their Engliſh boke to open my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries bothe to theyr owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and others.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The xxiij. probation.</head>
                  <p>Our men wyll nothinge but theyr engliſh booke, but the holy man Ireneus which dyd ſee. S Iohans diſciple (or as ſome affirme, whiche was ſcholer to
<pb facs="tcp:18399:61"/> S. Iohans diſciple named Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licarpus) doeth teſtifie that we muſt folowe the order of the tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ditions whiche the forefathers dyd leaue vnto them, vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they committed the cure of Chriſtes people: vnto whiche ordinaunces the very heathens (ſayth he) comming to Chriſtes ſtocke did obey, hauing their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefe written by the ſprit of God in theyr hartes, and not writen with ynke in velom or perche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. What ſhal we ſay then to theym whiche yet bewaile their Iewiſh ſcriptures plucked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poſtes and walles, &amp; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye deſyre theyr ſcripture with inke and paper in the booke? As for ſaluation only wryten in the hart by the holy ſpirit, it ſhould ſeme, they paſſe not of.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18399:62"/>
                  <head>The .xxiiij. probation.</head>
                  <p>The heathen Philoſopher would not youth to be the med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers with moral philoſophy, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were vnapte therun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, eyther to be Iudges therof, or to take any profyt thereby: and he ment not only youthe in yeares, but alſo in maners: a childe (ſaieth Eſaie) of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eth yeares old ſhal dye.<note place="margin">Eſay. lxv.</note> What then ſhal we ſaie ſhal we admit vnto the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dling of our heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly philoſophy whome the heathen thought vnmete, &amp; vnworthy to handle theyr lerning whiche was but prophane? woulde not the Iewes permitte all ages to the reading of all the bokes in the olde teſtament, and ſhall we chriſten men doe it? wyll we be worſe then the Iewes? Yea
<pb facs="tcp:18399:62"/> worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prophane ethnic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and more out of order? O Lord be mercifull vnto vs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .xxv. probation,</head>
                  <p>It was neuer admitted (though ſomtymes permitted) in any place of chriſtenedome ſcripture to continew in the vul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gar tongue, but only in tyme of ſciſme or hereſy, ſhall it nowe then be ſuffred to continew any longer in this realme, ſo many miſchefes yſſewyng therout as haue done daily increaſing theſe many yeares, and would do ſtyl more and more?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .xxvi. probation.</head>
                  <p>When it is in the vulgar tonge, the comen ſorte play with Gods worde, as the deuyll did diſputing with Chriſt, brought Gods worde, but to a wronge purpoſe. Chriſt ſaid man lyueth
<pb facs="tcp:18399:63"/> not only by breade, but by euery worde that procedeth fourth of Gods mouth. The deuill ſpake Gods worde, but it was not fourth of Gods mouth: ſo did the olde Prophete of Bethell ſpeake Gods word,<note place="margin">iii. Reg. xiii.</note> but not out of Gods mouthe. Likewiſe did the .CCCC.<note place="margin">iii. Re. xxii.</note> Prophetes whiche deceyued Achab. All ſorcerers, witches, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iurers vſe gods worde, but not oute of Gods mouthe: ſo haue all heretikes in tymes paſt, and doe at this day. But when is it Gods worde furthe of Gods mouthe?</p>
                  <p>Howe ſhall we know or proue that? Euer when it is ſpoken ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cording to the conſent &amp; faythe of the catholike churche.</p>
                  <p>For very ſcripture doeth ſhewe that the trew vnderſtandynge
<pb facs="tcp:18399:63"/> of Goddes worde, and that is furth of gods mouth ſpoken, is euer to be ſoughte in the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like churche, for the catholike church alone hath euer the true ſenſe of ſcripture, whiche is for that cauſe called of S. Paule the pyller and foundation of all trueth:<note place="margin">i. Timo. iii.</note> wherein alſo for this cauſe God ordeyned ſome apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, ſome Euangeliſtes,<note place="margin">Epheſ. iiii.</note> ſome Prophetes and teachers, ſtyl to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue, leſt we ſhoulde be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with blaſtes of errour. And therfore Ireneus wttneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,<note place="margin">Iren. li. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> and longe after him S. Auguſtine that the trewe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſcripture is to be hadde by the triall of the ſucceſſion of the holye biſhoppes and fathers ſince Peters time in the ſee of Rome, which thinge cauſed S.
<pb facs="tcp:18399:64"/> Auguſtine to ſay, I would not beleue the ghoſpell if thautori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the churche cauſed me not ſo to doe.<note place="margin">Aug. in epiſt. fund.</note> So that we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that hath been receyued of all men, at all times, and in all places of chriſtendome, and we muſte leane to thantiquitie, to the generalitie, and conſent of the fathers: and the true ſenſe and meanyng of ſcripture muſt euer be proued and tried oute herby. How be it to none of this our new men wil agre, becauſe it whollye maketh agaynſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but thei euer do ſtudie to bring al into queſtion &amp; to deny al ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral councels, all ordinaunces, decrees, canons, and expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcripture. And much of this diſorder thengliſh Bible doeth cauſe: wherfore me thinke
<pb facs="tcp:18399:64"/> it maye not well be permitted to continue.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The xxvij. probation.</head>
                  <p>Can it be choſen, but ſo long as all people haue the Byble in Engliſh at their pleaſure, there ſhal euer be ſome amonge them readie miniſters of the deuyl to diſpute, reaſon, and teache the reſidue, to the vtter deſtruction of all deuotion and good order? And yet amonge them ſelues they ſhall ſaye, the cauſe is they can not be taught truelye of the preachers abrode. And hereby hereſye ſhalbe ſowed plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, and Gods worde pitifullye abuſed vnder a colourable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe therof. Thei ſhal ſay: o the Ghoſpell ought not to be kept from chriſten men: and that is verye trueth: it oughte to bee
<pb facs="tcp:18399:65"/> taught them and preached vnto them, but not to teache them ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues for wraſtynge it amiſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The xxviij. probation.</head>
                  <p>It is the occaſion of manye hereſies to haue the ſcripture in the vulgar tongue. Howe be it hereſie dyd neuer ſpring furth of ſcripture, but only of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe vnderſtandynge of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (ſayeth Hilarius).<note place="margin">Hilar. lib. ij. de triuitate.</note> And yet then ſeing the rude ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſort be euer prone peruerſly to wraſt the ſcriptures, we muſte thinke that to haue ſcripture in engliſh, is to miniſter occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſorte to fall into errours· &amp; that it ſo ſhall doe appeareth by that they be not hable to weye nor beare the myſteries, nor to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the tropes and allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries whiche the greate learned
<pb facs="tcp:18399:65"/> men ofte are ſcant hable well to digeſte, howe much leſſe the cobler, carter, or coryer?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The ,xxix, probation,</head>
                  <p>Hilarius vpon <hi>In corde meo abſcondi eloquia tua</hi> Sheweth that the high myſteries oughte not to be publyſhed abrode a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge all people. It is good (ſaieth he) to hyde the kynges priuetie and ſecret. And ſ. Paul (ſaith he) was aferd to fede the people with any other but with mylke.<note place="margin">Math. xiii.</note> Chriſt in the goſpell tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth of ineſtimable treaſur fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and hid in the fylde that was bought:<note place="margin">Math. vii.</note> and of the precious ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes not to be caſt before ſwyne, nor the holy vnto dogges. &amp;c. What doeth all thys but plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye forbydeth thee Byble in Engliſhe or the myſteries therof
<pb facs="tcp:18399:66"/> to be ſet abrode?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The ,xxx, probation,</head>
                  <p>Lyke as GOD appointed tholde lawe to bee written in ſtone, tables, or boke, ſo did he appoint (as Hieremie witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth) the new to be writen only in the heart of man.<note place="margin">Hier. xxxi.</note> Why ſhould the writing in bookes then be ſo highlye regardyd? But this carnall, this fleſhly regardyng by no meanes can be ſo well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate or rather quyte taken awaye, as by taking the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture fourth of the vulgar tonge and fourth of thandling of the lewde ignoraunt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The ,xxxi, probation,</head>
                  <p>God appointed the Goſpell onelye to be writen in the hert of man. And therfore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels did fulfyll theyr office con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb facs="tcp:18399:66"/> this matter, in that thei only wrote theyr epiſtles to the people being abſent, but euer taught by mouthe theym that were preſent, as appeareth to the Corinthians, where Paule ſaith: othere thinges,<note place="margin">i. Cor. xi.</note> when I come and am preſent, I wyl or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: And .S. Iohn. ſayde,<note place="margin">Epiſtle .ii.</note> I had mani thiges to write, which I wil not write, but tel you and teache you mouth to mouth.</p>
                  <p>The ſame teachinges then and many other haue bene receiued in the Church euin as it were by hande, and ſo continued ſtyll and ſhall doo, tholye ghoſt tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching frome tyme to tyme, as Chriſte promiſed, if the Bible were ones taken forthe of the ignorauntes iudgementes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The ,xxxij, probation.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18399:67"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">i. Timoth. i.</note>Paule writeth to Timothe rebukynge many whiche then woulde preſume to be doctours and teachers not mete for that office: but how many thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des be in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Engliſh teachers now, yea rather ſeducers and only ſowers of hereſies through the englyſh tranſlacion muche worſe and more ignoraunt then they of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Paule then ſpake?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The ,xxxiij, probacion.</head>
                  <p>Yf it be laufull for all to haue the handeling of ſcripture, then made not tholy ghoſt a iuſte di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion of giftes appointing but ſom doctours and teachers and thother to be taught: Yea and Chriſt cald in vain the Apoſtles and theyr ſucceſſours the ſalt of thearth, &amp; the light of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, if euery one that wyll ſhal haue
<pb facs="tcp:18399:67"/> that office, as no doubte they haue had this longe tyme, and wyll haue ſtyl, if it ſhoulde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in Engliſh, which GOD forbyde-</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .xxxiiij, probacion.</head>
                  <p>Gregorius Nazianzen ſaieth, <hi>Oportet paulatim infirmis fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ea que perfectiora ſunt ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rire, &amp;c.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Greg. Nazian. concione de ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritu ſancto.</note> We muſt by lytle and litle open the ſecretes of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to the infirme chriſtians. How can it be ſuffred thenne to be in englyſh for euery one too open it to him ſelfe?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The ,xxxv, probation.</head>
                  <p>Paule would all to be taught the ſcripture: and therfore he wrote his epiſtles to al: but not all to deſcant vpon them. For then he would not haue ſaide,<note place="margin">i. cor. xiiii.</note> if any be thought to be a prophet
<pb facs="tcp:18399:68"/> let him know what I write vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .xxxvii. probacion.</head>
                  <p>Moiſes did committe the boke only to the priſtes &amp; not to the people.<note place="margin">Deut. xxxi.</note> And the prieſt was euer made iudge in hard cauſes of the ſcripture.<note place="margin">Deut. xvii.</note> But our men wil be iudges them ſelues: &amp; where lerned they that? euen of the deuil the autour of arrogancy. God ſaid in Deut. he that will not obey in this to the preiſte,<note place="margin">Deut. xvii.</note> ſhall ſuffer death. But what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedyence woulde the engliſhe readers geue to the preiſt? yea to the higheſt Prieſt of all in earth vnder Chriſt?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The xxxvij. probation.</head>
                  <p>S. Baſil biddeth be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that ye blabbe not out the holy myſteries, nor ſuffer them
<pb facs="tcp:18399:68"/> to be defiled with prophane eyes, but ye ſhall rather bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayed to handle them: yea, ye ſhall reuerence the hydde my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of God with ſpirituall and not corporall beholdynges, and kepe them not touched nor to be handled of the rude, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt, and common people. What can be more playne then this againſte the Byble in the vulgar tongue?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The xxxviij. probation</head>
                  <p>O howe manye ſcrupules and doubtes haue ſpronge in manye mens heades (whiche neither they nor their fathers euer imagined before) through the ſcripture in Engliſhe? How many alterations, ſciſmes, and deuiſions amonge the ſimple haue ryſen, yea betwene man
<pb facs="tcp:18399:69" rendition="simple:additions"/> and wyfe, maiſter and ſeruant? How manye women heretikes haue taken vpon them thoffice of teachinge hereby in theſe ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res paſte,<note place="margin">Women he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes.</note> and all contrarye to Paules doctrine?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The xxxix. probation:</head>
                  <p>Amonge other, one of the greateſt inconueniences that hath theſe wretched yeres ſpro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g by hauing the Byble in engliſh, is this, that many, yea very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye, God beſt knoweth, haue preſumptuouſlye taken vpon them beinge yet moſte vnmete thervnto, thoffice of doctours and teachers in corners and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenticles, beinge not ſent, but arrogantly and preſumptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, ſaying, God did ſend them, and they woulde ſeke for none other ſending, howe be it they
<pb facs="tcp:18399:69"/> did not marke the plague of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias kyng of Iuda for vſurping thoffice of the prieſt, whervnto he was not called. They did not marke howe Chriſt being very man did choſe the xij.<note place="margin">Math. x Luc. x.</note> Apoſtles and lxxij. diſciples, and ſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> furth, where ye ſee bothe the outwarde choſynge and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſendyng.<note place="margin">Actes. i.</note> Mathias was outwardlye by men choſen to ſuccede Iudas: and ſo were the ſeuen deacons outwardlye cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led:<note place="margin">Actes. vi.</note> and thactes the xv. it hathe pleaſed tholye ghoſt and vs &amp;c. Beholde here bothe the inward and outward ſending. And the holye ghoſt ſayde,<note place="margin">Actes. xiii.</note> ſeperate me Paule and Barnabas, &amp; they put theyr handes on them and ſente them furthe. Here ye ſee outwarde ſendynge. Yea, and
<pb facs="tcp:18399:70"/> Paule ſayeth:<note place="margin">Rom x.</note> howe ſhall they preache except they be ſent?</p>
                  <p>Nowe yf we ſhoulde take onely inwarde ſendinge without the outwarde, then the Churche coulde neuer bee certayne who were ſent and who were not.</p>
                  <p>Agayne Chriſt appoynted cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Apoſtles, doctours, and teachers &amp;c. Whiche order, ſaith Paule,<note place="margin">Epheſ. iiii.</note> ſhall continue in the church for euer. But the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it muſt nedes be that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche ſhal ſtil appoynt them as they did then &amp;c. Moreouer he that ſhall be called to the office of a prieſt or byſhop muſt haue a good report of them whiche are without.<note place="margin">i. Timo. iii.</note> Marke here the outwarde ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. And S. Auguſtine ſayth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if becauſe Thappoſtles were taught of god,<note place="margin">Aug. in prolo. li. de doct. Chri.</note> none own ought
<pb facs="tcp:18399:70"/> to bee outwardelye called or taughte, then (ſayeth he) lette none reade the goſpel, nor none heare ſermons. Paule had tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ghoſt and yet he went not to preache tyl Ananias had layde his handes vpon him.<note place="margin">Actes. ix<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> He was ſent (ſayth he) to man to receiue the ſacramentes and to be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the church. Neuertheles all might be done and wrought onely inwardlye by thangell or ſpirite of God: but then ſhoulde neuer be any certayntie. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God hathe ordeined that like as in temporal gouernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce none is made ruler but beynge outwardly ſent and appointed by men, euen ſo in the ſpirituall functiones. Wherfore nowe to conclude, ſeing the only remedy to redreſſe this damnable er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<pb facs="tcp:18399:71"/> of theym whiche teache ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly and do<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> much hurt in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners through the engliſh tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is to take it awaye (for by other meanes it wil not be ſtopped) it can not be permitted that the Bible ſhoulde continue in engliſh. Here in this I might haue had iuſt occaſion to ſpeake againſt preachers which hadde authoritie (wickedly geuen) to preache, and did comenly preach vnderſtandinge not the latine tonge (as it was ſaide) but were called ſome from one occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, and ſome from another, and ſome frome plaieng the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces parte in enterludes: but I wil not medle with this matter</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The ,xl, probation.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Hierom. in Ezech. <hi>44.</hi>
                     </note>S. Hierom ſaith, <hi>Alta, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>funda dei myſteria non ſunt mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtranda
<pb facs="tcp:18399:71"/> vulgo, nec proferenda ad populum, ne ſi maiora ſe audie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint, maieſtatem ſcientiae ferre non poſſint, &amp; quaſiſolido ſuffocentur cibo, qui adhuc lacte infantiae nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triendiſunt.</hi> The depe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founde myſteries of God are not to be ſhewed to the common people, nor to be vttred to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: leſt they hearinge greater thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges then they can beare, be not hable to atteyne to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge therof: and be as it were choked with harde meate, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che yet oughte to haue been fed but with milke of infancie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .xli, probation.</head>
                  <p>It helpeth well and is a good probation againſt the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Bibles that Chriſte euer vſed paraboles to the rude vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned ſorte: yea and that
<pb facs="tcp:18399:72"/> the wordes of the goſpell do te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie that ofte when he ſpake they vnderſtode hym not: <hi>Nihil (inquit) horum intellexerunt:</hi> but yet he ſaide to his diſciples and theyr ſucceſſours: <hi>Vobis datum eſt noſse myſteria:</hi> It belongeth to you to knowe the myſteries: Yea and whan he would teache theym high ſecretes, he aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into the mount from the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men people, wherof Eſai hadde ſpoken.<note place="margin">Eſay. vi.</note> Ye ſhall heare with youre eares and not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. &amp;c. In expounding which place. S. Hierom doeth vtterly dryue awaye the comen people from medling or handlyng the myſteries of ſcripture. Agayne doeth not Chriſte ſhowe in the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Luc. xii.</note> that he is a good ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arde, which geueth in meaſure
<pb facs="tcp:18399:72"/> to the ſeruauntes theyre meate in dewe ſeaſon? what a wicked ſtewarde were he then, whiche withoute all meaſure or diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, obſeruing no order, regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding no mans perſon or bloode, wold ſet on the table before all men indifferently, were he Lord or lorell, maſter or ſeruaunt, all kyndes of diſſhes at ones bothe groſſe and fyne?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .xlij, probation.</head>
                  <p>Chriſoſoſtom vpon,<note place="margin">Chriſoſt. lib. iiij de ſacerdotio.</note> 
                     <hi>Intende lectioni. i. Ti. iiij,</hi> ſheweth thoffice of Biſſhops to be to ſtudye the ſcripture, &amp; thoffice of the laitie to know the ſcripture by theyre teaching and preaching ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for theyr ſaluation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .xliij, probation,</head>
                  <p>S. Auguſtin ſheweth certen places of ſcripture to be for preg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunt<note place="margin">Auguſt. epiſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Voluſiam.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18399:73"/> wittes, and certen for the rude &amp; dolardes: But how then can the ſcripture be in thengliſh tongue for all indifferentlye to reade?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The ,xliiij. probation.</head>
                  <p>O how many Englyſhe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders doe take hurte of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes and canticles not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing the myſteries, nor when it is a trope? not knowyng when it is to be taken to the lettere, and when the letter doth kylle?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .xlv. probation.</head>
                  <p>Gregorius Nazianzen ſaieth <hi>I is conuenit de rebus diuinis diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">lib. i. ſuae theol<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>qui contemplandi acumine coeteris antecellunt. &amp;c.</hi> It is mete for theym too intrete of Gods myſteries, whiche doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede and paſſe other in excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of gyfte, &amp;c, But then it ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:18399:73"/> not be lawfull for euery one to haue it in the vulgare tonge.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The ,xlvi. probation.</head>
                  <p>S. Hierom ſaith that the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes dydde not permitte any to reade the beginning of Geneſis,<note place="margin">In proaemi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> E<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chielis.</note> nor the canticles, neyther the beginning nor the ende of Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiell before .xxx. yeares. And the Romayns ſuffered none to rede the bokes of Sibylla but onlye the tenne commiſſioners named <hi>decemviri,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Feneſtella. lib i. capi. xiii.</note> and before theym the .ij. commiſſioners na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>duumviri,</hi> So muche re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they gaue to theyr boke, And ſhall we chriſtians ſuffer the hyghe myſteries to be miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably tormoyled of all handes? But ye wyl ſay: S. Hierom and Chriſoſtom alſo in certein pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſeme to allow the laitie vnto
<pb facs="tcp:18399:74"/> reading of ſcriptures: And. S. Hierom did tranſlate ſcripture vnto the Dalmatians. Truth is, many thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges for a time haue ben permitted of deuotion, but after ſeing the ſucceſſe nought, they haue been taken awaye. After the beginninge, maydes, wiues, boyes, and men kept vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gils together aboute martyrs tumbes: and Vigilantius for reprouing it was ſharply taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of S. Hierom: yet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for inconuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces it was taken away.<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib vi. cap. xxxiij.</note> And at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge the bodie of Chriſt was geuen to the laytie in their han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to carye home. &amp;c. But tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough witchecraftes and other abuſes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, that cuſtome was taken awaye. Likewyſe the laytie receyued once vnder
<pb facs="tcp:18399:74"/> bothe kindes, whiche cuſtome throughe offenſes and perils that chaunced, and that might chaunce ſtill, is iuſtly prohibited and taken awaye vtterlye. And likewiſe anſwere is to be geuen to all them that make theſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to haue the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures in engliſhe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .xlvii. probation.</head>
                  <p>If that which Euſebius doth teſtifie in his time to be trewe, had been nowe verified in theſe our daies, we neded not then to be ſo ferd of hauinge ſcripture in euery mans hand.<note place="margin">Libro eccl. cap. xvi.</note> His wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des be theſe. <hi>Imperiti obſeruant ne diſputare audeant de ijs quae ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, et de illis teſtimoniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibere quae neſciunt.</hi> The vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned euer obſerue this, that they dare not once diſpute or reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:18399:75"/> of thoſe thinges that thei be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt of, nor beare teſtimonie of thoſe thinges whiche they know not. But alas nowe the more ignoraunt, the more obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in madde boldneſſe, ſo that by no meanes thengliſh tranſla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion maye be ſuffered.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .xlviij. probation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Scripturarum intelligentiam non ex propria praesumptione, ſed ex maioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcriptis &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toritate ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur quos et ipſos ex apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolica ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e intelligendi re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gula<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuſcepiſse conſtabat, Haec Euſebi. lib. xi. Eccl. cap. ix.</note>The example of Grego. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zian. and Baſil be to faythfull chriſtians a ſufficient rule to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, which if we do, we wyl ſay awaye with thengliſhe Bibles, away, they can not be abiden.</p>
                  <p>For the readers therof paſſe of no expoſitions of the fathers, but onlye ſtycke to theyr owne bare taking of ſcripture as thei phancye it, and as they pleaſe: where as theſe .ii. holy doctours ſtudied ſcripture together, not
<pb facs="tcp:18399:75"/> preſumptuouſly folowing their owne imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but folowing the doctrine and authoritie of the elders, whom they knew to haue receyued the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of ſcripture euyn by ſucceſſion from the Apoſtels.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The xlix. probation.</head>
                  <p>If Spiridion iuſtlye repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended Triphillius but onelye for chaunginge of one worde in ſcripture (<hi>cubile</hi> for <hi>lectu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi>) what reprofe are our men worthye,<note place="margin">Lib. i. Tripere. capit. x.</note> whiche chaunge many hundred wordes, yea ſentences and all? If holy Baſilius wold not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer one ſyllable of ſcripture to be corrupted or altered,<note place="margin">lib. vii. tripert. cap. xxxvi.</note> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would haue ſuffered many deathes, what ſhall we then ſay
<pb facs="tcp:18399:76"/> to the great and damnable cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and alteration that hath been among our men? If holy Baſilius bad the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors coke medle with his coke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye &amp; let ſcripture alone,<note place="margin">tuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt (inquit) de pulme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tarijs cogitare, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dog mata diuina de coquere lib. vij <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rip. ca. xxxvi.</note> what woulde he haue ſayde to oure men theſe yeres paſt?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="probation">
                  <head>The .l. probation.</head>
                  <p>Hauinge the ſcripture in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe cauſeth manye braynles bodies to diſpute and reaſon they know not whervpon, and euer to lay ſcripture for the wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kedlye, as al heretikes euer did, where as in dede in reaſoninge with ſuche, ſcripture wyll not ſerue.<note place="margin">Tertull. de prae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcrip. haerettcoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et lib. iiij. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rtionem.</note> For as Tertullian ſaieth, in diſputing with an heretike we muſte not flee to ſcriptures, nor
<pb facs="tcp:18399:76"/> pitche our battel there: for ther eyther neuer or els very hardly the victory ſhalbe gotten. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes wylbe ouercome (ſayeth Siſinius vnto Nectarius in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtorie of Socrates <hi>li.</hi> 9. <hi>trip. ca.</hi> 19) nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther with ſcriptures nor w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations<note n="†" place="margin">Approbata ab <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ccleſia no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> opor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tet rurſus rati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>onibus fulcire etc. Nam que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> par eſt ſpiritui fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cto et Cbriſto diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, ita in ſuis inſtitutis eſt ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua authoritas &amp; poteſtas: Nec minus ratu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt quod eecleſia dicta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te ſpiritu ſancto tradidit qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod ipſe tradidit. Haec Cypri. de Lot. ped.</note> but only by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the churche, and by the traditions of the fathers &amp; elders. So that beſide the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture written we muſte receyue manye traditions not written: many generall councels in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holye ghoſt did ſpeake: and ſundrie interpretations vpon ſcriptures made by the holy fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers beinge repleniſhed wyth Gods ſpirite.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb facs="tcp:18399:77"/>
               <head>¶The concluſion of this ſimple diſcourſe.</head>
               <p>SEing now theſe probations which be euident againſt the ſcripture in Engliſhe: ſeing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the great hardnes that is in ſcripture with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſes therof, and how many waies the letter doth kyl: And ſeing againe that the vniuerſall churche of Chriſt hath vtterly forbid the ſcripture to be in the vulgare tongue, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſideryng the manyfolde incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences that ryſe therof, as great numbres of hereſies, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, and contempt of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, with fleſhely libertie &amp;c. And finally, ſeing that by no meanes ſo ſoone as by the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in engliſh, hereſies do both ſpryng daily, and be alſo main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined, wherin ſhould good men
<pb facs="tcp:18399:77"/> be more diligent than in thexter patio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hereof? wherfore it ſhalbe euery faithful chriſtians duetie, being in authoritie, to lay to his healping hande to the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way quite (&amp; that with al ſpede) the Engliſhe tranſlations with all hereticall Engliſhe bookes, whiche no doubt haue been the greateſt occaſion of all the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheifes we haue hadde in this realme of late dayes. Through theſe, our newe founde religion hath euer ſtrongly been main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined and vpholden. Our new found religion (I ſay) which ye muſt nedes confeſſe to haue ben ſtarke nought and damnable, becauſe the beginnyng was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutry, the continuaunce extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; the ende plaine treaſon. Yea, &amp; euen from the beginning
<pb facs="tcp:18399:78"/> their procedinges (for ſo they termed them, beyng rather wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy the name of retrocedinges) were ſtyll from ſynne to ſynne: Fyrſt,<note place="margin">Peccatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod per paenite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deletur ſuo pon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dere ad aliud peccatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grauius trabit: Et hoc ſuppliciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni longe omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt grauiſsimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>catu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per aliud p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nitur, quod peccatur quum in profundu <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerit, conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nit.</note> forſaking the head of the churche, falling from the vnitie therof: then deſpiſing all gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall counſelles, all ordinaunces fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning kept through out chriſtendome: After this ſpoyling, pollyng, pylling, rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and ſtealing all landes, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namentes &amp; goodes of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che (being more fearſe then euer was Iulian thappoſtata) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mercy or pitie: And finally ſpytefully contemninge all the holy ſacramentes, with all cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and iudgementes of the churche and fathers vpon ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, only ſticking to their own, what pleaſed them to phanſie.
<pb facs="tcp:18399:78"/> O lorde, was not this a tyme moſt miſerable? Ieſu be mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto vs, and graunt vs ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to fall againe into the lyke palpable darkenes.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶Of Maſſe &amp; all other diuine ſeruice in the churche to be in Latine and not in the vulgare tongue.</head>
                  <p>ANd here note further (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche you) that like as it is nowe ſpoken of ſcripture not to be in Engliſh, euen ſo is it ment that as vnlawful it is (yea and more too, if more may be) that the high myſteries in the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Maſſe or other diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uice ſhould be in Engliſh: where as the preiſt is a comon perſon and offereth vp for al the people beyng the meane betwene God and them, ſo that his communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
<pb facs="tcp:18399:79"/> is to God, and not to the people. What cauſe is there then why diuine ſeruice ſhould be in Engliſhe, except ye thynke that God vnderſtandeth no Latine? Neither the Italians nor Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s haue diuine ſeruice in their vulgare tongue. Moreouer, at that tyme of diuine ſeruice all the comen people then preſent, ſhuld onely put their whole affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce <hi>in fide ma<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ris eccleſiae</hi> in the fayth of oure mother the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke churche: like as our beleif is in the baptiſme of infantes. Yea, &amp; note further, that it was not without great myſtery the writyng of Chriſtes tytle at his paſſion in Hebrewe, Greke, and Latine. Alſo it was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great myſterye that many wordes were neuer tranſlated,
<pb facs="tcp:18399:79"/> as <hi>Alleluya, Oſanna, Amen, Saba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth, Kirieleiſon &amp;c.</hi> And that Chriſt praied in ſecret &amp; ſilence alone, the head for the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>die, to ſignifie vnto vs thereby, that the prieſtes office is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to doe the ſame, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon miniſter for al the people, being meane betwene God &amp; them. As for that of Paule to the Co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rinthians,<note place="margin">i. Cor. xiiii.</note> which might appeare to the ſimple to make for theyr purpoſe to haue all in the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar tonge, yf ye marke it well, it is onely ſpoken for them whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che doe preache, expounde, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprete ſcriptures in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church: that is to ſaye, that their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, their expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinges, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſcriptures (they beinge authoriſed therevnto) muſt euer be made in that to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge
<pb facs="tcp:18399:80"/> whiche the hearers doe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande and perceyue.</p>
                  <p>And this (ye know well) bothe is and euer hath ben vſed. And therfore here now further, A man might demaunde a queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherfore ye com to the Churche I ſuppoſe ye wyll ſaye (as ye muſte no doubte, yf ye tell the treuthe) that the chiefe intente of your comming is or ought to be, to pray (though ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and diuine ſeruice, and the miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of the holy ſacramentes be cauſes alſo) ſeing that Chriſte called the Church the houſe of prayer,<note place="margin">Luc. xix.</note> bringyng for him the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of Eſaie: and ſeing alſo we haue in ſcripture ſo manye notable examples concernynge the ſame purpoſe.<note place="margin">Luc. ii.</note> Anna the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetiſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued day and night
<pb facs="tcp:18399:80"/> in the temple in faſtynge and prayer:<note place="margin">Luc. xxiiii.</note> the Apoſtles after Chriſtes aſcenſion remayned ſtyll in the temple in laudyng and bleſſyng God: Peter and Iohn went vp in to the temple at the ninth houre of prayer:<note place="margin">Actes. iii.</note> Salomon beſought GOD to graunt the petition of all that prayed in the temple:<note place="margin">iii. Re. viii.</note> and Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel beinge a priſoner in Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,<note place="margin">Dan. vi.</note> euer loked toward the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when he prayed, vppon his knees thryſe in the daye. This ſuerly doth proue that the chief intent of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to the churche ought to be to praye. But all this tyme which now (thankes be to God) is paſt, hauynge the diuine ſeruice in Engliſhe was an extreme enemie to all godly prayer and deuotion. For then
<pb facs="tcp:18399:81"/> men phanſied ſo to heare what was redde (ſtriuing ofte ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon in ſimple iudgemente) that feruente prayer whiche ought to be, was ſmally regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And here now for this time I make an end beſechig al god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye people (as for Momus his iudgement I paſſe not of) well to accepte this my labour: ſeing that herein is nothinge ſpoken but that whiche hath bene taught for treuthe and beleued of al men, in all places, and at al times ſince y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> primatiue church: ſeing alſo that herein we leane onely to the generalytie of all chriſtendome to the antiquitie of the elders whiche haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it as it were by hande euyn tyll this day, and to the conſent and agrement of all the holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:
<pb facs="tcp:18399:81"/> Whoſe wittes were as muche as our new mens, theyr dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as great, theyr lerning greater, theyr ſtudye more fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, theyre deuotion hotter, theyr nombre more, theyr conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuaunce longer, they alway ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for catholikes (but thother euer for heretikes) alwaye la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boring and ſtudiyng that might be whollye to the profyt of the churche of Ieſus Chriſte: To whome, with the father, and the holye ghoſt, be all honoure and glorye, for euer and euer.</p>
                  <closer>AMEN.
<signed>
                        <hi>Memor<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>e nouiſſima:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eccl. vii.</note> 
                        <hi>&amp; in aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num non peccabis. <hi>I. S.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:18399:82"/>
            <head>A PRAYER.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>IESV</hi> God and man we beſeche thy Maieſtie,</l>
               <l>Of meſureles mercie tender our miſerie,</l>
               <l>Haſt to helpe, that helpe haſt in thy hande,</l>
               <l>Ne ceſſe with thy <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> repaire this Ilande,</l>
               <l>Suffer not Satan and his curſed progenie</l>
               <l>To bewitche thy people with ſciſme and hereſie</l>
               <l>And ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs O God of power &amp; puiſaunce,</l>
               <l>Neuer to quaile throughe thy gracious gouernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</l>
               <l>Dede and worde in vs ſo proportion</l>
               <l>Infinitly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we acknowledge thy heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>Snared we were and nigh ſnatched to confuſion</l>
               <l>Sciſme and hereſie preuailing in this region.</l>
               <l>Haue thankes and praiſe for our reſtitution.</l>
               <l>As we may and can we muſt and wyll willingly</l>
               <l>Vvaking and ſleping exalte thy Maieſtie.</l>
               <l>Thy mercie for our ſelues as we aſke and haue,</l>
               <l>Haue like mercie we humblie crie and craue</l>
               <l>On Philip and Mary, graunt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy mercie</l>
               <l>Reigne, peace, and power in longe life &amp; felicitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Autoris nomen libri no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcribitur huius,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vt placido vultu quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> probaret opus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Plus circa nome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>quam</ex>
                     </expan> veru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plebs ſtomochatur,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I is adhibens ſolum, qui placuere, fidem.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:18399:82"/>
            <head>¶Fautes eſcaped the printer in many of the bokes.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Leafe.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Syde.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Lyne.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A.v.</cell>
                     <cell>ij.</cell>
                     <cell>.iiii. reade, ofte hurteth.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>C.viii.</cell>
                     <cell>i.</cell>
                     <cell>in the marge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, math .ix</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>D.v.</cell>
                     <cell>i.</cell>
                     <cell>xvii. rede, Actes</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>E.iii.</cell>
                     <cell>i.</cell>
                     <cell>xv. put oute.,.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>E.iiii.</cell>
                     <cell>ii.</cell>
                     <cell>in the marge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, Iac. iiii.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>H.vii</cell>
                     <cell>i.</cell>
                     <cell>in the margent writte,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="3">Iren. lib. tertio. capit. iiii.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>I.i.</cell>
                     <cell>i.</cell>
                     <cell>i. rede, and it is.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>I.i.</cell>
                     <cell>ii.</cell>
                     <cell>v. rede, that which hath</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>I.ii.</cell>
                     <cell>ii.</cell>
                     <cell>xviii. reade, doe, apereth</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>I.vi.</cell>
                     <cell>i.</cell>
                     <cell>xx. rede, Altercations,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>I.vi</cell>
                     <cell>ii.</cell>
                     <cell>xxii. rede, ſending, Howe</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>I.vii.</cell>
                     <cell>ii.</cell>
                     <cell>xxii. rede, none now.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
